Yoshio nozawa
Yoshio Nozawa
The Central Research Institute's
The Central Research Institute's
International Research Center for International Studies
International Research Center for International Studies
will begin.
will begin.
Let's welcome Director Wang Yu
Let's welcome Director Wang Yu
to give us a round of applause.
to give us a round of applause.
Good evening, everyone.
Good evening, everyone.
Let's welcome Director Wang Yu
Let's welcome Director Wang Yu
Today we are pleased to invite you to our Earth Institute
今天我們很高興請到我們地球所的
This special review researcher Dr. Zhao Feng
這個特評研究員趙峰博士
come talk to us
來跟我們講
Our little friend of the earth, the moon
我們地球的小夥伴月亮
then let me briefly introduce
那我簡單介紹一下
Background information of our presenter today
我們今天主講人的背景資料
Dr. Zhao was born in Hualien
趙博士是出生在花蓮
He graduated from the Department of Physics, National Taiwan University.
那是臺大物理系畢業的
after that in san diego
那之後就在聖地亞哥
UCCNL gets a Ph.D. in Earth Sciences
UCCNL拿到地球科學的博士
That's also NASA.
那也在美國太空總署就是NASA
many years of service
服務了很多年
Then in 2006 he
之後他在2006年
That's because Taiwan is running a space agency
那因為臺灣正在進行一個太空機構
undertake a large project
進行一個大型的計畫
So we are very happy to have him back
也這樣我們非常高興的邀請他回來
He is also at Chuo University
他也在中央大學
Before coming to Academia Sinica
在來中研院之前
He is the Dean of the Faculty of Earth Sciences at Central University
他是在中央大學地球科學院院長
for a few years
做了幾年
He has been in Academia Sinica for four years
他到中研院已經四年
Dr. Zhao's expertise is in Earth and planetary dynamics
趙博士的專長是在地球跟行星動力學
gravity
重力學
And geophysics, seismology, etc.
還有地球物理 地震學等等
This is also the research scope of our Earth Institute
這也是我們地球所的研究範圍
he is on earth
他在地球所
he also does
他還做
Because of the background I just introduced
因為剛剛我介紹的背景
He also does space vehicle geosciences
他也做太空車地學
In terms of research, of course, there is no need to drop the order here
研究方面當然不用在這裡在這裡墜序
But he is invaluable
不過他難能可貴的是
Apart from this research
這個研究之餘
he also for
他還替
I think there is a scientist in China
我覺得國內有一個科學人
It is the Chinese version of Scientific American
就是 Scientific American 的中文版
Often write Chinese articles there
常常在那裡撰寫中文的文章
Also published a book on the ancient and modern world between heaven and earth
也出版了一個天地間古今世
If you are interested in his speech
如果大家對於他的演講有興趣
What we can look forward to in the future is the scientific people
那可以以後期待的就是在科學人
He also often writes
他還會常常寫
Okay then I'll stop talking nonsense
好 那我廢話少說
Please listen carefully to this moon
就請大家好好仔細聽這個月亮
Is this sound okay?
這樣聲音可以嗎
Can
可以
sure
可以啊
Thank you Vice President
謝謝副院長
Just now the vice president mentioned that those are research expertise
剛才副院長講到那些是研究上的專長
Of course he's really good at storytelling over here.
他在這邊當然真的專長是講故事
Today is
今天是
Today is Uncle Zhao telling a story
今天是趙叔叔講故事
Today we're on a meet-the-neighbors tour
今天我們一個認識鄰居之旅
This neighbor is our neighbor
這個鄰居是我們大家的鄰居
moon
月亮
We all know this neighbor
這個鄰居我們都知道
Every day actually you have the chance to see him
每一天其實你都有可能有機會看到他
But thousands of years of human civilization have seen thousands of years
但是人類文明幾千年也看了幾千年
I really don't know him
其實真的不了解他
until recently so to speak
一直到最近的可以說
Only after the development of science did we slowly understand him
科學發達以後才慢慢慢慢了解他
Today I will of course talk in depth
今天我當然會深入講一些
things we already know
我們已經了解的事情
But it's really just fur
不過真的還只是披毛而已
real
真的
We can really say that we are to our neighbors
我們真的可以說我們對我們的鄰居
I still don't know
還是知念不知心
let's take a look
我們先看一下
Everyone see me here
這個大家看到我這個裡面
actually asked a lot of questions
其實問了很多問題
i hope i have time
我希望有時間
Can cover these problems
都能夠cover到這些問題
Some questions are not easy to ask
有的問起來都不太好問
Because really we know so little
因為真的我們知道得太少了
This is what we are all familiar with
這個是我們大家都熟悉的
the moon looks like this
月亮就長這個樣
After a whole month's cycle
經過一整個月的循環的話
We can see this before and after
我們前前後後可以看到這樣
if there is no cloud
假如沒有雲的話
It can be said that we only know
這個是可以說我們只知道
only see its ID
只看到它的身份證
we don't really understand it
我們其實並沒有真的理解它
This can be obtained from
這可以從
I'll be back here later
待會我就回到這裡
Our understanding of the moon from the ancients
我們從古人的對月亮的理解
you can help it imagine
你可以幫它想像一下
Really, actually, I feel full
真的其實我覺得都滿
I feel sympathy for the ancients
我對古人覺得都滿同情的
they really don't know
他們真的不知道
what's going on in this world
這世界是什麼回事
then we now think
然後我們現在認為
Primary school textbooks tell us
小學課本都有告訴我們
But the ancients really didn't know
但是古人真的不知道
They are the moon that sees the sun
他們就是看到太陽的月亮
Cycle like this every day for centuries
每天這樣循環 世紀
He really doesn't know what's going on
他其實真的不知道是怎麼回事
The same should be true for the moon
對月亮應該也是這樣
to the ancients
對古人的時候
Ours is in the poetry, in the legend
我們的在詩歌裡面 傳說裡面
And these cosmology legislation
還有這些宇宙觀 立法裡面
all have the shadow of the moon
都有月亮的影子
But it's just a superficial impression
但是都只是一個浮面的一種印象而已
So of course this is over
所以這個當然就是過去了
this meeting
這個會議
another example
另外一個例子
For example, in the Yijing
譬如說在意經裡面
These universal philosophies that everyone is familiar with
大家都熟悉的這些宇宙哲學
two of them
其中的兩儀
The moon is one of the two instruments of nutrition
月亮就是兩儀 營養的其中之一
This is when we used to try to understand these things
這都是我們過去想要嘗試去理解這些東西的時候
invented some
發明出來的一些
we know it's not true
我們知道不是真實
not scientifically correct ideas
不是在科學上不是對的一些想法
We are now going to look at it from a scientific point of view
我們現在要用科學的角度來看
when our neighbor
我們的鄰居的時候
The first thing to actually ask is that we just call it the moon.
第一個其實要問的是我們就叫它月球
you know it's a ball
你也知道它是球
In fact, I really want to ask why is it a ball?
其實真的要問是為什麼是球
Do you think this will be a problem?
你說這個會是問題嗎
Isn't the earth also a ball?
地球不是也是球嗎
Isn't the sun also a ball?
太陽不是也是球嗎
yes these things are balls
對 這些東西都是球
Actually, one physics question we can really ask is
其實我們真的可以問的一個物理問題是
why is this stuff a ball
為什麼這些東西會是一個球
There's actually a lot of physics behind this.
這個其實裡面有很多還是物理的道理
I point it out just to say
我把它點出來也只是說
when we really want to understand this neighbor
我們真的想要理解這個鄰居的時候
We don't even know what it looks like
連它長相我們都不知道過去
don't know why
都不知道是為什麼
It's all taken for granted
都是覺得理所當然就是這樣
Is it a matter of course?
是不是理所當然不見得
because in the solar system
因為在太陽系裡面
there are many smaller things
有很多小一點的東西
The so-called small these few examples
所謂小 這幾個例子
For example, there is a little star
譬如說有小遊星
This is a photo taken with a real small spaceship
這是真的拿小的太空船去拍到的照片
or the moon of mars
或者是火星的月亮
Mars has two small moons
火星有兩個小月亮
one of them looks like this
其中有一個也長這個樣
this is very small
這個很小
It's about tens of kilometers in size.
大概就幾十公里這樣大
Such a thing is really not round.
這樣的東西還真的不是圓的
We say a circle is not a ball
我們說圓不是 是球
This little thing is really not a ball
這種小東西還真的不是球
That is to say, in Sun Creek
也就是說在太陽溪裡面
or in this universe
或者這個宇宙裡面
when something comes together
一些東西聚在一起的時候
Only when it is large enough will it become spherical
只有夠大以後才會變成球狀
the moon is big enough
月亮是夠大
Something about a few hundred kilometers will probably
大概幾百公里的東西大概就會
something this big
大概這麼大的東西
It will probably naturally become spherical
大概就會自然會變成球狀
The reason behind that is actually very simple
那背後的原因其實很簡單
It's the same as water flowing downhill.
就跟水往低處流是一樣的道理
lowest failure state
叫做最低未能狀態
This is what it means
這個講起來就是
It has turned into this tree in one fell swoop and the rain comes out
一下就已經變成這個樹雨就出來了
I'm the reason behind this
我這個是背後的道理
That is to say you see the sun as a ball
就是說你看到太陽是球
The moon is a ball, the earth and we are also balls
月亮是球 地球我們也是球
In fact, behind
其實背後都有
physical reason
物理的原因
it's just saying
這只是說
point out one
點出來一個
things we take for granted
我們覺得理所當然的事情
It's not a matter of course
其實不是理所當然
ok let's move on to some
好我們繼續看一些
related to the moon
跟月亮有關的
just on the surface we can
只是表面上我們就可以
Some interesting phenomena observed
觀察到的一些有趣的現象
I'll go into it later and talk about some comparisons
待會兒我再進入講一些比較
A more in-depth understanding later
後面比較更深入的理解
Let me tell you one
先講一個
I want to spend a few minutes on this
這個我想花幾分鐘
Tell everyone this long-winded
跟大家這個囉嗦一下
our this
我們這個
The so-called force in life
生活中間的所謂力
Whether it is the calendar
不管是年曆月曆
powerful anyway
反正都有力
This thing is done in units of years
是以年為單位做的這個事情
we all know
我們大家都知道
There is a so-called Gregorian calendar
有所謂陽曆
There is a so-called lunar calendar
有所謂陰曆
The Gregorian calendar follows the sun
陽曆就是跟太陽來
according to the sun
根據太陽定的
We are all familiar with this force by now
我們現在都是熟悉的這個力
is the power of the sun
就是太陽的力
Something to do with the moon
跟月亮一點關係
nothing
都沒有
it really doesn't matter at all
真的一點關係都沒有
For example we are in
譬如說我們在
This is like the old days
這個好像是過去那種
A kind of traditional society will use
傳統社會才會用的一種
one of determination
定力的一個
One way is called two-style solar term
一個方式叫做二式節氣
right
對不對
I might give you this now
我現在可能給你們這個
this self
這個自己
ask yourself this
這個問一下自己
See the second type of solar term
看到二式節氣
Do you think it's positive or negative?
你覺得這是陽力還是陰力
This is actually going to
這個其實要
Now you have to define what Yang Li is
你現在要定義一下什麼叫陽力
what is yin force
什麼叫陰力
I'm talking about Yangli now
我現在講陽力就是
we usually get that day
我們平常拿到那個日子
The moon force is the yang force
那個月力就是陽力
And you know the day is fixed by the sun
而且你知道一天都是用太陽來定的
right
對不對
one day to the next one day to the next
一天到下一天一天到下一天
It's natural that it takes a day
這個很自然就是用一天
use the sun
用太陽來定
Does it have nothing to do with the moon?
跟月亮沒有關係嘛
such a force
那樣的一個力
Yangli
叫陽力的話
The second type of solar terms is Yin force
二式節氣是陰力
Is it really Yangli?
還是真的就是陽力
the answer is
答案是
Because you need to know the function of the 24 solar terms
因為你要知道這個24節氣的作用
it actually puts the sun
它實際上就是把太陽
We orbit the sun more than 365 days
我們繞太陽365天多
Divide that day into 24 parts
那個日子把它分成24份
Each one is about 15 days more like this
每一份大概15天多這樣子
That's it
就是這樣
it divides the year
它就是把一年去分
This has nothing to do with the moon
這個講到現在跟月亮都沒有關係
right
對不對
Look at these words in these 24 solar terms
你看這24個節氣的這些字眼
you can also see
你也可以看出來
It's full of temperature effects
它充滿了是溫度的效應
The effect of humidity
溼度的效應
Effect of sunlight
日照的效應
Relationship to the middle of the sun's orbit
跟太陽軌道中間的關係
None of the words have anything to do with the moon
沒有一個字跟月亮有關係
one more you can know
還有一個你可以知道的
In fact, all you know is
其實你就知道的是
these solar terms
這些節氣的日子
The month and date are the same every year
幾月幾號每一年都是一樣的
it didn't run around
它沒有跑來跑去
For example, tomb-sweeping day
譬如說清明節
April 4th or 5th
4月4號或5號
there is a new day
就有台新的一天
because our days have no years
因為我們日子有什麼任年
That day beats a little bit
那日子有一點點會跳動
basically it's the same day
基本上它就是同一天
All these solar term days are on the calendar
所有的這些節氣的日子在日曆上
It's the same day every year
都是同 每一年都是那一天
Does this already tell you that this is the Gregorian calendar?
這就已經告訴你這是洋曆嘛
Because the moon doesn't matter, right?
因為月亮沒有關係嘛 對不對
even if you think about it
甚至你再往回想一下
What is the purpose of thrift
節氣的目的是什麼
actually an agricultural society
實際上是農業社會
He wants to know me every year
他想要知道我每一年
what time do you want to do
要到什麼時候想要幹什麼
what you do is agriculture
你幹的事情就是農業
That agriculture has nothing to do with the moon
那個農業跟月亮一點關係都沒有
right
對不對
You have to completely follow the law of the sun
你完全要按照日太陽的這個規律
to farm
去種田
you survive
你才活得了
If you use what moon
假如你什麼用什麼月亮的
Cloudy and sunny
陰晴圓缺
If you plant, do your farming
你去種 去做你的農業的話
You'll be almost 20 in a few years
大概沒幾年你就快20了
because the time is wrong
因為時間都不對了
If you look at it from this angle
這個從這樣的一個角度看的話
Calendar
洋曆啊
It's Nongli
就是濃力啦
I'm not wrong, there shouldn't be
我也沒講錯應該沒有
Really, if you want to do farming
真的你要做農業的話
don't think about the moon
你不要去想月亮
you really have to follow the sun
你真的要跟著太陽幹
All these things follow the sun
這些所有東西都是跟著太陽來的
That is to say, even without the moon
也就是說即使沒有月亮
this is still right
這個都還是對的
So how does this follow
所以這個怎麼會跟
anything to do with the moon
任何會跟月亮有關係
Does it have something to do with sound?
跟音力有關係呢
Absolutely not
完全沒有
So this is Yangli
所以這個是陽力
Then don't we really have something called sound power?
那我們真的不是也有一個叫音力的東西嗎
Do you know what Nongli and Yangli are?
濃力跟陽力你知道是什麼了
Of course we have the so-called sound
當然我們有所謂音力
Sound itself doesn't really matter.
音力其實本身沒有什麼作用
It's just a fun and a convenience
它只是一個好玩一個方便
Do you remember when the moon was full last month
你記得你是幾月上個月月圓的時候
Actually the moon is full again
其實又月圓了
you just have this
你只是有這種
there is such a rule
有這種規律
Actually it's not doing anything
其實它沒有在做什麼事情
Unless you are some aquatic creature by the sea
除非你是海邊的什麼水生物
to do your life cycles according to the tides and stuff like that
要根據潮汐來做你的生命的週期之類的
or you don't
要不然你根本
appointment has nothing to do with you
約量跟你沒有關係
So that's a chestnut
所以那個是陰栗
We know of some very conscious
我們知道的有一些很有意識的
like three verses, right?
像三節對不對
that's a chestnut
那個是陰栗
That's why
也就是這樣的原因
you are using the legislation of the chestnut
你在用洋栗的立法
inside that stand
那個立裡面
These chestnuts
這些陰栗
You know it's different every year, right?
你知道它每一年都不一樣對不對
because it is not chestnut
因為它不是洋栗
the ancient people
那古時候的人
or now you get
或者現在你拿到
Is there any so-called peasant power?
所謂農民力有沒有
it is counted in black chestnut
它是用陰栗來算的
so it becomes saying
所以變成說
The knotter is jumping up and down on that stand
結器在那個立上是跳來跳去
different every year
每一年不一樣
Because the two stand cannot be combined
因為這兩個立沒有辦法合起來
Because this is not an integer multiple
因為這不是成整數倍的
you will definitely be jumping around
你絕對會跳來跳去的
so this
所以這個
I put this first
我先把這個
Let me remind you of the role of the moon in this
這個月亮的在這個裡面的角色跟大家提醒一下
really so
真的是這樣
For example, when we talk about the Lunar New Year
譬如說我們講農曆年
In fact, the word does not seem to be wrong
其實這個詞好像其實沒有不對
Is January 1st the lunar year?
農曆年就是一月一號嘛
Because it's the lunar calendar?
因為是農曆嘛
Is the lunar calendar the solar calendar?
農曆就是陽曆嘛
When we talk about the lunar year, we actually talk about the lunar year
我們講農曆年其實是講陰曆年
this is just a thought
這個只是一想一想
There is indeed such a
這確實是有這樣的一個
can be fun
可以算有趣吧
here
這裡
We are still looking at some of the moon
我們還是在看月球的一些
some of what we can see
我們可以看到的一些
some interesting things on the surface
表面的一些有趣的事情
you will notice this heaven
你會注意到這個天上
There are two eyes and a smiley face
有兩個眼睛一個笑臉
Do you remember this day?
大家有沒有記得這一天呢
Photos taken on December 2, 2008
2008年的12月2號拍的照片
This is when the sun is going down
這個是太陽正下山的時候
Of course it's Crystal
這當然是晶星
This is the lunar calendar and I ran to this position
這個是農曆也跑到這個位置
That day, this day, this time, here
那一天這一天這個這個時候在這裡
Isn't it a lot of fun to have a cartoon performance here
是不是一個很有趣的一個卡通效能在這裡
let's pay attention
我們注意一下看
when you see the moon
你看到月亮的時候
This is Yueya we saw
這個是我們看到的月雅
because the sun is here
因為太陽在這邊
So there's no problem with the light here
所以這邊照了亮沒有問題
In fact, it seems that there are also
其實好像這邊也有
The places that are not illuminated are not illuminated
不亮的沒有被照掉到的地方
Look closely, there seems to be something
仔細看好像也有東西
right
對不對
I'm sure someone has this experience every day.
我相信有人每天都有這種經驗吧
Take a closer look at the time when the weather is clean
你仔細去看那個天氣很乾淨的時候
When you look at Yueya
你看那個月雅的時候
It seems that the audio and video can also see the whole moon
好像影音也可以看到整個月亮
This is in the photo
這個是照片裡面
Because it can be exposed to light for a longer time
因為它感光時間可以長一點
see more clearly
看得更清楚一點
Let me show you another example
我再給大家看另外一個例子
This is also in the photo
這也是照片裡面照到
take longer
感光久一點
It really seems like the sun is shining here
真的好像太陽在這邊照
Not here at all
完全沒有照到這邊
but here it seems
可是這邊好像
But it's bright anyway
但怎麼也是亮亮的
faintly visible
隱隱約可以看到
This is a clearer example
這個是更清楚的一個例子
this is not the full moon
這個不是滿月
Sputnik
是用人造衛星
It was taken from the spaceship
是用太空船上面照的
dark side of the moon
月球的陰暗面
This moment is when it shines on the dark side of the moon
這一瞬間是它照月球的陰暗面
That is to say, when the sun actually shines on Naimian
就是說太陽其實照的是耐面的時候
I can actually see it glowing
居然可以看到它在發亮
This is actually
這個其實是
i think a lot
我想很多
Everyone has this experience
大家有這個經驗
This is actually called a ground photo
這個其實叫做地照
is the earth
是地球
This is light bouncing several times
這個是光反射好幾次
The sun shines directly on the bright side of the moon
是太陽直接會照到月亮那個亮的那一面
yes
沒錯
it can't see this side
這一面它照不到
But why is this side slightly brighter?
但是這一面為什麼會隱隱約有一點亮呢
It's the sun's light that shines on the earth
是太陽照到地球上的光
the earth reflects it back
地球把它反射過去
brighten it up
把它照亮了
Then the reflected light
然後那個反射的光又
reflected back into your eyes
反射回來到你眼睛裡
Or the one seen in the machine
或者照樣機裡看到的那個
very interesting
很有趣啊
Light and shadow have gone several times
光影走了好幾次
I can still vaguely see it
居然還隱隱約約可以看到
this is not your illusion
這不是你的錯覺
is really there
是真的有
Taiwan has relatively humid air
台灣因為空氣比較潮濕
when you see this phenomenon
看到這個現象的時候
not many
並不是很多
OK there are still some phenomena
OK 還有一些現象
probably more or less familiar
大概也都多少都熟悉的
date and time
日時
one thing is very interesting
有一件事情滿有趣的
yes it's a coincidence
是這是一個巧合
It is the moon and the sun in our sky
就是我們天上的月亮跟太陽
Of course the sun is big
當然太陽很大
but the sun is far away
但是太陽很遠
But to observers on Earth
可是對地球上的觀察者
these two circles
這兩個圓圈
almost as big
幾乎一樣大
sometimes a little farther a little closer
有時候稍微遠一點近一點
will be big
會大大小
that's basically the same size as it really is
那基本上真的一樣大
it's a coincidence
這很巧
That's why if you encounter
就是為什麼假如說碰到有
Just enough to cover the whole land from the sun
給整個把地的太陽剛好遮遮到
Sometimes the distance is slightly worse
有的時候距離稍微差一點
it will be slightly smaller
它會稍微小一點點
more and more more and more real
又越來越 越來越環實
This is very obvious to tell you this coincidence
這個都是很明顯的告訴你這個巧合
At this distance on Earth these two things appear
這兩個東西在地球上的這個距離看起來
It's really as big as a conspiracy
真的是陰謀一樣大
Here is an example
這是一個例子
If seen from space
假如從太空裡面看
this is earth
這是地球
This is the astronaut on the International Space Station
這是在國際太空站上面的太空人
Full time of a day captured by a camera
用照相機照到的一個日全時
an image on earth
在地球上的一個影像
a shadow
一個影子
In other words, this black lump is the shadow of the moon.
也就是說這個黑黑的一坨就是月亮的影子
That is to say, the people in this
也就是說人在這個裡面的人
When I looked up to the sky, I saw this
當時抬頭往天上看就會看到這個
This is because the earth is also rotating
這個因為地球也在轉
The moon is running, the sun is running too
月亮也在跑 太陽也在跑
This shadow is of course in the net mother's
這個陰影當然在網母的
direction is moving fast
方向在很快的移動
So someone at a certain location will see
所以在某一個布定點的人會看到
The moon is here to block the out of tune
月亮來擋住走調
that is to say on earth
也就是說在地球上
Who is the person who sees the moon and sun?
看到月日時的人是什麼呢
people in this strip
是在這個條帶裡面的人
I don't know where this is going at this time
我不知道這個時候這個是往哪裡走
Call this strip something like this
叫這個條帶是這樣
people down here look up
在這底下的人抬頭看
then you will see this
當時就會看到這樣
This is what we look at from another angle
這個是我們從另外一個角度去看
This thing I think everyone compares
這件事我想這個大家都比較
In fact, everyone understands
其實大家都了解了
just bring it
只是把它拿來
recall
回憶一下
OK
OK
This is a fast motion video
這個是快動作的影片
that's one month
這樣就是一個月
like this for a month
這樣一個月這樣
I miss everyone
這個我想大家
It can be said that I have seen too much, right?
可以說我看多了對不對
But when you slow down, maybe you see something that you don't normally notice
但是放快的時候也許你看到一些好像你平常不太會注意到的事情
For example, what was your first feeling when you saw this
譬如說你看到這個第一個感覺是什麼
Of course, we all understand the ups and downs.
當然這個陰晴圓缺我們都懂了
Why does it seem to be dangling?
為什麼好像在晃來晃去的有沒有
this dangling is not it dangling
這個晃來晃去不是它晃來晃去
because when we were on earth
是因為我們在地球上的時候
Did you know it's orbiting the earth?
你知道它在繞地球嘛
The orbit around this one is not a circle, it's an earth circle.
這個繞的那個軌道不是圓喔是土圓喔
It's a little earthy round
有一點點土的圓喔
This is known to oil lamp mechanics
這個是油燈力學都知道的
If the orbit is round
那個軌道土圓的情況下
How can it be a little slower when you are far away?
遠的時候會比較怎麼稍微慢一點
Walks a little faster when approached
靠近的時候會稍微走快一點
That is to say, when we look here
也就是說我們在這邊看的時候
The moon is actually sometimes faster and sometimes slower
月亮其實有時候快一點的時候慢一點
then you speed it up
那你把它放快一點
Sometimes I can see a little more of this side
有時候我可以多看到這邊一點
Sometimes I can see a little bit more from the angle
有時候我在角度可以多看到這邊一點點
i shake it together
我把它晃弄在一起
just see it like it's dangling
就看到好像它在晃來晃去
not he shaking
不是他在晃
just the way we see it
只是說我們看的角度
It's been changing a little bit like this
有一直在稍微有點點變這樣子
That's actually the main reason I'm posting this for everyone to see.
那其實我放這個給大家看的主要原因
not this
並不是這個
but want to ask everyone
而是想問大家
what is the most important thing you see
你看到最重要的一件事情是什麼
except he is round
除了他很圓
we already know he's round
我們已經知道他很圓
a little wobbly
有一點點晃
know him
還知道他
you know what's most important to you what you see
你知道你最重要你看到的是什麼
The most important thing you really see is
你真正最重要看到的是
where you didn't see
你沒有看到的地方
did you notice you didn't see behind him
你有沒有注意到你沒有看到他後面
He is just a face for you to see
他就是一張臉給你看
He won't let you look behind
他不讓你看後面
this strange thing
這個很奇怪的事情
You see I brought props
你看我帶了道具來
This is our earth
這是我們地球嘛
we live up there
我們就在住在上面
Just earn and die
就跟著賺就死
Earn a lap a day
一天就賺一圈嘛
the moon is here
月亮在這邊
27 days to transfer full circle
27天多轉移整圈
Because there is also the relationship between the angle of the moon and the sun
因為還有月亮太陽角度的關係
So the sun and the moon move
所以太陽月亮也動了
So more than 27 days is not really the cycle we see
所以27天多還不是真的我們看到的這個週期
We really use the cycle of cloudy and sunny to be 29 and a half days
我們真的用陰晴圓缺的週期是29天半的樣子
So there are two kinds of moons
所以陰力有兩種月
about 30 days about 29 days
大約30天小約29天
Because the average is 29 and a half days
因為平均是29天半
this is not important
這個不重要
it is important to say
重要的是說
this moon is orbiting
這個月亮它在繞
It doesn't matter that the earth is spinning on our own
地球我們就是自己在轉沒關係
when it is winding
它在繞的時候
it never showed you the back
它從來沒有把背面給你看過
it goes around like this
它是這樣繞的
that's all
就這樣
It seems to say that it is hiding behind you, so don't dig it.
好像說它後面躲著你就不要挖你看
You haven't read it, right?
你沒有看過後面對不對
but someone has seen
但是有人看過
This is a new jigsaw puzzle
這是前面重新一張拼圖
The back looks like this
背面長這個樣
I'll come back later
我等下再回頭講
why doesn't he let you see
為什麼他不讓你看
not him
不是他
He looks like this on the back
他背面長這個樣
Actually you just look at this
其實你光看這個
you can see the front
你就可以看到正面
let's face it
我們就要正面吧
This is called the back
這個叫背面
English is called near sides
英文叫near sides
near face and far side
近的面跟far side
the far side
遠的那一面
In fact, you have already seen this
其實這個你已經看出來
It's different, right?
不太一樣了對不對
There are many reasons behind this
這個後面有很多原因的
The moon is billions of years old
這個月球幾十億年的
in this career
這個生涯裡面
These rear impact craters
這些背面撞擊坑
It's the impact crater for food.
就是運食的撞擊坑
are still well preserved
都還保存得很好
front of earth
地球正面
This side of the crater
這一面撞擊坑
Many are called by this black
很多都被這種黑色的叫做是
In fact, volcanic rumors
其實火山流言物質
almost covered
差不多蓋掉
why is this
為什麼會這樣
this is another question
這是另外一個問題
this is
這個是
There are different theories trying to explain it
有不同的學說想要去解釋它
But at least we see that's the case
但是我們至少看到現象就是這樣
everyone has seen this
這個每個人都看過
How many people have seen this?
這個有幾個人看過呢
There should be 21 people who have seen it
應該有21個人看過
Why did 21 people see who
為什麼21個人看過是誰
These people are collectively called Apollo workers.
這些人統一叫做阿波羅特工人這樣子
Because really 1969 all the way to 1972
因為真的1969年一直到1972年
The American moon landing program is called the Apollo program
美國登月計畫叫阿波羅計畫
do you all know
大家都知道嗎
A total of 7 times
一共去了7次
3 people each time
每一次是3個人
7 times succeeded 6 times
7次成功了6次
The so-called success is later
所謂成功就是後來
2 out of 3 people land on the moon
3個人中間有2個人登月
like walking on it
在上面走過路那樣子
then pick it up
然後再接回來
6 successes
成功過6次
In other words, 12 people walked on the moon
也就是說有12個人在月亮上走過路
21 people all flew to the moon
有21個人都飛到月亮去
flew from behind
從後面飛過去過
he saw it with his own eyes
他親眼看到過
This is one of the princes
這個就是其中某一個太公人
take a picture of him and show us
把他拍下來給我們看
I said seven times
我說去了七次
only succeeded six times
只成功了六次
what happened again
還有一次怎麼回事
That's Apollo 13
那是阿波羅第13號
A total of seven times from the 11th to the 17th
一共從11號到17號去七次
No. 13 didn't work out
第13號沒有成功
you may remember
大家可能有記得
have filmed
有拍過電影
It's called the Apollo 13 movie.
就叫阿波羅13號那個電影
great worth seeing
很棒 很值得看到
He just failed to land on the moon
他就是沒有成功的登月
but he also flew
但是他也飛到
fly behind to go around
飛到後面去繞過
rounded the moon
繞過月球了
In the temporary that oxygen level exploded
在臨時那個氧氣平爆炸
he can't go on
他沒有辦法繼續下去
very delicate
很很精弦的
let him bring him back successfully
讓他把他成功的把他帶回來
so that time was
所以那一次是
still lucky
還算是幸運
let's go back to this one
我們再回到這一個
why doesn't he let you look behind
為什麼他不讓你看後面
This is still the two pictures just now
這還是剛剛那兩個圖
this is special
這個就特別講
this is
這個是
Of course this color is painted by man
這個顏色當然是人畫的
His painting shows that
他這個畫的顯示的是
The third highest and the deep valley
第高三跟深谷
high and low terrain
有高低而地形
moon shape
月形
OK
OK
the thing I just talked about
剛才的講的那件事情
In fact, such a thing
其實就是這樣一件事情
you see him the same
你看他同一點
To describe it is
在形容一下就是
he has a rotation period
他有一個自轉周期
exactly the same as the revolution period
像公轉周期完全一樣
let's say seven days
不如說七天
no matter how many days
不管是幾天
he is the same
他就是一樣
what does it mean
意思是什麼
when he is circling
他在繞的時候
He only has one face facing the words
他只有一個面在朝的話
when he makes a full circle
他整個轉一圈的時候
He turned around by himself
他自己自轉了一圈
did you notice
你有沒有注意到
he like this
他這樣
is the public transfer circle
是公轉移圈
At the same time, this time is the full circle of self-transfer
也同時這個時間是自轉移整圈
these two cycles
這兩個週期
exactly the same time
一模一樣的時候
For us, for people on earth
對我們來對地球上的人來講
it is a facing earth
它就是一個面朝的地球
this hasn't said why
這還沒有講為什麼
just to tell you
只是告訴你
Just described the same phenomenon again
又把同一個現象形容了一遍而已
So my question is
那我要問的問題是
Is this a coincidence
這是巧合嗎
how could it be such a coincidence
怎麼會這麼巧呢
Of course it's not a coincidence
當然不是巧合
for example
譬如說
the moon to the earth
就是月亮對地球
if this is jupiter
假如這個是木星
jupiter has a bunch of moons
木星有一大堆月亮
Jupiter has now been calculated to have sixty moons
木星現在已經算出來有六十幾個月亮
a few of them are larger
其中幾個比較大的
It's something we've known since the days of Homeoire
是我們從家裡略的時代就已經知道的
all those moons are like this
那些所有的月亮都是這樣
it's all like this
都是這樣
no matter how close
不管是近的
Far
遠的
it's all like this
都是這樣
don't let you look behind
不讓你看後面的
so it's no coincidence
所以這不是巧合
there must be some reason
這一定有什麼原因
of course not
當然不是
not when gods created the world
不是有神造世界的時候
he likes it
他喜歡這樣
of course not
當然不是
but
但是
what is the reason
那到底是什麼原因
Here is a very simple diagram
這裡有一個很簡單的圖
But I know I can't go too deep into it
但是我知道不能講太深入進去
But roughly, let me describe to you
但是大致上我給你形容一下
The reason behind this is called North Korean friction
這個背後的原因叫做朝系摩擦
There are North Korea and friction
有朝系還有摩擦現象
it will end up like this
最後就會這個樣
and tell you a story
然後講一段故事給你聽
That
那
The so-called DPRK friction can be described like this
所謂朝系摩擦這樣子形容吧
This is our earth this green
這個就是我們的地球這個綠綠的
This is the middle point is the North Pole
就是這個中間點就是北極的
look like this
這樣子看啊
let's see from above
我們從上面看啊
we see it this way
我們這樣子看
isn't the earth spinning
地球不是在轉嗎
The earth rotates like this
這個地球就這樣轉
is the farther one is farther away
就是越遠的一個越遠
Normally you can imagine saying
正常情況下你可以想像說
It would be great if this blue was sea water
這藍的假如是海水好了
you think of it as sea water
你把它想像成海水
Normally you would want to say
正常情況下你就會想說
the moon is here
月亮在這邊
So the water is sucked up
所以水被吸 高起來了
yes
沒錯
when the moon works
月亮當工的時候
The sea should have a high tide
海水應該是有高潮的時候
On the other side it will actually rise up
在對面居然也會高起來
This place is actually far from the moon
這個地方離月亮其實是
farthest place
最遠的地方
How could it also go out high?
怎麼會也會往外高出去呢
This is because of centrifugal force
這個是因為離心力
I won't go into it in particular.
我就不特別講深進去
It's sharp and centrifugal
就是有犀利跟離心力
When the two balance
兩種達到平衡的時候
we just one day
我們就一天
there will be two tidal bulges
就會有兩個潮汐的凸起
Do you see what this bulge means?
你看這個凸起是什麼意思
you are the one who lives on earth
你是住在地球上的人
You follow the earth around once a day
你跟著地球一天轉一圈
the moon is here
月亮在這裡
When you follow the moon to this place
你跟著月亮轉到這個地方的時候
you'll find this place is now orgasm
你會發現這個地方現在是高潮
highest water level
水位最高
you keep turning
你繼續轉
half a day later you transferred here
半天以後你轉到這裡了
You found the water dripping down here again
你又發現水這邊滴下去
Then it's high again
然後這邊又高起來
That is to say, the tide creek rises and falls twice a day
也就是一天潮溪漲弱兩次
because you are turning
因為你自己在轉
But actually the moon is also slightly within the day
但實際上月亮也稍微在這一天之內
also moved a little
也動了一點點
So it's not exactly twice a day
所以也不是說剛好一天兩次
a little over twice a day
是一天多一點兩次
that time is
那個時間是
In terms of this phenomenon
以這個現象來講
In fact, it will happen twice in 24 hours, 0510 minutes
其實24小時0510分鐘之內會發生兩次
Just once every 12 hours and 05 minutes
就12小時05分鐘一次這樣
This is the Chaoxi that we normally know.
這個是我們正常知道的潮溪就是這樣
Of course there are some other
當然還有一些其他
tidal constellation of its cycle
它的周期的潮汐座
I think I won't talk about it here
我覺得這邊就不講了
The most important thing about this is this
那這一個最主要的就是這樣
That means you go to the beach to see
也就是說你到海邊去看
you sit there longer
你在那邊坐久一點
sit for a long time
坐個大半天
you will see the ebb and flow
你會看到潮起潮落
you can see twice
你可以看到兩次
this is ideal
這是理想狀況
but it's not
但實際上不是這樣
actually kind of weird
實際上有點奇怪
in fact you are not
實際上你不是
these two blue bumps
這個這兩個藍色凸起
is attracted to the moon
是被月亮吸住的
fixed this direction
定好了這個方向
But the earth must rotate underneath
但是地球在底下一定要轉
isn't the earth spinning
地球不是在轉嗎
it must turn
它一定要轉
There's friction here
這個地方就有摩擦力
This picture is also fun
這個這張圖也很好玩
This picture is from the Internet when I leaked it
這張圖是我從網路上當漏下來
This color is not what I ordered
這顏色不是我訂的
But when I talk to students
可是我跟學生講的時候
I suddenly found out
我突然發現
I'm describing blue, green, friction
我在形容說藍的綠的有摩擦
it's wired
好奇怪
people have friction
人家有摩擦
when rubbing
摩擦的時候
You see you are speaking to the earth
你看你對地球來講
Since there is friction
既然有摩擦
He wants to drag him away
他是想扯著他走
He pulled him more and more
他又越讓越拉著他
He tried to pull him away again
他又轉想把他拉走
The result is a little bit like a slant
結果是有一點點像斜掉了
It doesn't matter if it's slanted or not
那不管斜不斜掉
anyway there is friction
反正這裡有摩擦
When there is friction, you know that energy is being consumed
有摩擦你就知道能量在消耗
In fact we have many of these
實際上我們有很多這種
The idea is to say
想法方法是說
use tidal power
用潮汐發電
In fact, the principle of tidal power generation
其實這個潮汐發電的道理
actually
實際上就是
Turn this friction directly into heat energy
把這個摩擦直接變成熱的能量
Go through our phone first
先經過我們的電
use up
用掉
finally become hot
最後還是變成熱
Let's use it in the middle
中間我們就使用它一下
that's where this energy comes from
那就是這個能量的來源
In terms of the earth
以地球來說來講
turn out
結果是
Slower and slower
越轉越慢
always look like this
一向看是這樣
These two are there like brake pads
這兩個像煞車皮一樣在那裡
I'm at the bottom, I insist on turning
我在底下我硬要轉
Isn't that getting slower and slower?
那不是越來越慢嗎
so
所以
Judging by this phenomenon
以這個現象來看
First
第一個
This is tidal friction
這是要潮汐摩擦
It causes a phenomenon called
它造成了一個現象叫做
The earth is turning slower and slower
地球越轉越慢
this
這個
you don't know right
你不知道對不對
yes
有啦
your parents and children
你爸媽小朋友
Have your parents talked about it?
爸媽都有講過嗎
days are getting harder
日子越來越難過了
Do you have
有沒有
the days are getting longer really
日子越來越長真的
how is the day
日子長到什麼樣子呢
we are now 24 hours a day
我們現在一天24小時
In fact, every day is different
其實每天都不太一樣
long time watching
長期在看
Because of this tidal friction phenomenon
因為這個潮汐摩擦的現象
you say the number is small
你說這數字很小
I tell you
我告訴你
I'll show you how small it is
我形容給你看有多小
today if say
今天假如說
we are so long today
我們今天是這麼長
a hundred years ago
一百年前的
Today should be a little shorter than now, right?
今天要比現在應該短一點點嘛 對不對
Aren't we turning slower and slower?
我們不是越轉越慢嗎
So that time will be a little shorter
所以那個時候會短一點點嘛
How short is it?
短多少呢
Only a thousandth of a second short
只短才會千分之一秒而已
You say it's nothing
你說這個沒什麼嘛
that's all
就這麼一點嘛
do i just worry
我只要擔心嗎
will i know
我會知道嗎
you don't have to worry
你也不用擔心
you won't know
你也不會知道
But precision scientific instruments can measure
但是精密科學儀器是可以量出來的
so what
那又怎麼樣了
nothing wrong
也沒怎麼樣嘛
ok let's continue the story
好 我們故事繼續講
Scientific instruments are boring anyway.
科學儀器反正就是很無聊嘛
Since I think the earth is turning slower and slower
既然我覺得地球越轉越慢
I can't measure it either
我也量不出來
I can't go directly
我沒有辦法直接去
not so accurate
沒有這麼準的
A hundred years ago there were no good clocks
一百年前也沒有很好的鐘
what to do
是怎麼辦呢
There are clever ways to find this kind of evidence
有聰明的辦法來找這種證據
this is an interesting rumor
這是一個很有趣的傳聞
What about this story?
這個故事呢 要講日權石
For example, this is the earth
譬如說這是地球上嘛
If a certain time over the sun stone
假如某一次越日權石
We just saw that one of those dark shadows
我們剛看到那個那個黑影的那個
If it is said that the sun power stone at that time
假如說那一次的日權石的
The trajectory is like this
走的軌跡是這樣
That is to say, in this yellow belt
也就是說在這個黃帶裡面
Everyone will see that day
所有的人那天往頭上都會看到
Sunstone looks like this
日權石這樣子
This is a real event
這個是真的一次事件
This is an example of what I'm talking about
這是我講這個是一個例子
This example is
這個例子是
136 BC on a certain day
西元前136年某月某日
There should have been a Sunstone
應該有過一個日權石
and there really are
而且真的有
Because this example is inside the records of Babylon
因為這個例子是巴比倫的記錄裡面
There was no pen and paper in Babylon
巴比倫那時候也沒有紙筆
And engraved on that clay tablet
而且刻在那個石泥板上
air pattern paper
氣形紋紙
found inside fire pipes
在火管裡面可以找到的
It is recorded that this day
這裡面有記錄說這一天
It really happened that day full time
那天真的有發生日全時
And that's how it was seen in Babylon
而且在巴比倫看到就這樣
it's his record so what
這是他的記錄就怎麼樣
then we are now saying
那我們現在就是說
I said scientists are so boring
我說科學家這種無聊嘛
it will be fine
就會好吧
That day has happened this day full time
那一天有發生過這個日全時
I now have a way to recover that full-time full-time moon
我現在有辦法來復原那支月日全時
because we now know the position of the moon to the sun
因為我們現在知道月亮的太陽的位置
And I know how it turns
而且我知道它是怎麼轉的嘛
i rewind time
我把時間倒帶
Rewind over 2000 years
倒帶2000多年
use the computer to calculate
就電腦去算
Just do the math
回算就是了
Counting to that day more than 2000 years ago
算到2000多年的那一天真的
That day the real moon is between the earth and the sun
那一天真的月亮是在地球跟太陽中間
really full time
真的有日全時
but sorry
但是對不起
Babylon can't see that day full time
那個日全時巴比倫看不到
The place to see should be here
看到的地方應該是這裡
The barbies are here and they are tired
巴比人在這兒,人家很累
what will happen
會發生什麼事情
really full time
真的有日全時
But people who saw him said he was in the Babi people
可是看到的人說他在巴比人
We now count back to the computer
我們現在電腦回頭算說
impossible
不可能
what went wrong
發生什麼錯誤了
because when we arrive
因為我們到代的時候
Use 24 hours a day to turn the earth back
使用一天24小時把地球往回轉
But it's not really 24 hours a day
可是真的不是每天都24小時
It used to turn faster
以前轉得比較快一點
you have to follow that
你要按照那個
The length of the day that changes a little bit turns back
稍微改變一點點的日子的長度往回轉
When you turn to the day more than 2000 years ago
等到你轉到2000多年那一天的時候
really that strip goes through the barbies
真的那個條帶會經過巴比人
is so
是這樣
then we now
那我們現在
This seems to become
這個好像就變成說
records of people at that time
當時的人的紀錄
can be used by me now to do
可以被我現在用來做
To make a proof is to say
做一個證據是說
It's true that the earth is turning slower and slower
真的地球有越轉越慢
and slow down
而且轉慢的
That level is really what I just said
那個程度真的就是我剛剛講的那個
That is from modern experience measurement.
那個是現代的經歷測量裡面出來的
This is actually found in the historical records
這個是歷史的記錄裡面居然可以找到
Evidence that the Earth is growing slower
地球越展越慢的證據
this is awesome
這個很厲害
there is one more strange thing
還有一個一樣奇怪的事情
What I just talked about is thousands of years old
剛剛講的是幾千年的事情
Of course, the earth is not only a few thousand years
那地球當然不只幾千年
Earth is 4.6 billion years old
地球活了46億年
Shouldn't it be turning faster earlier?
那更早以前不是應該轉更快嗎
how do i... is there any way to know
那我怎麼...有沒有辦法知道呢
This is another interesting observation
這又是一個很有趣的觀察結果
here is an amplifier
這裡一個放大機
Prototype mirror to see
原型的鏡子要看到的
a coral it grows
一種珊瑚它會長
Are corals living things?
珊瑚是生物嘛
animal president
動物會長
This kind of coral can still be found
這種珊瑚現在都還找得到
you know how long it is
你知道它怎麼長
it is every day
它是每一天
it will secrete a layer
它就會分泌一層
this skeleton
這個骨骼
one lap a day
一天就一圈
but winter and summer
但是冬天跟夏天
Secretion varies in width
分泌的寬度不一樣
maybe the temperature is different
也許溫度不一樣
so it
所以它
I don't know how much winter will be
我不知道是冬天會多
grow faster
比較長得快
Or it will grow faster in summer
還是夏天會長得比較快
but
但是
its
它的
grow out
長出來了
between this day
這一天一天之間
Qualification to this is one year
資格到這個是一年
Qualifying to this is another year
資格到這個是又一年
It's another year to qualify for this
資格到這個又是一年
How many bars are there in the middle?
中間有多少條呢
you can count
你可以數啊
you are under the magnifying glass
你就放大鏡底下
Counting under a circular mirror
用圓鏡底下去數
you don't want to count
你不想數
just ask your students
就請你學生
public reading birth number
公讀生來數
inverse number
反正數
you will know
你就可以知道
Eh
欸
how many days in a year
當時的一年有幾天
can't it
不是可以嗎
this
這個
This is another example
這個又是一個例子
this is
這個是
400 million years ago
四億年前的
one
一個
painted rock specimens
畫石標本
There are many such specimens
這種標本很多
different ages
不同年齡
I only ality
我只ality
Let me show you, 400 million years ago, this is very recent
我給你看,四億年前,這是很最近的
Because the earth is 4.6 billion years old
因為地球有四十六億年
This is only less than one-tenth of the recent
這只是最近十分之一都不到
four hundred million years
還是有四億年很久
The result of this subordinate is
這底下屬的結果是
At that time, there were about 400 days in a year
那個時候一年有四百天左右
What does it mean?
這是什麼意思?
We now have three hundred and sixty-five days in a year
我們現在一年有三百六十五天
At that time there were four hundred days in a year
那個時候一年有四百天
What's the meaning?
什麼意思?
This year, this will not change
這個一年,這個不會變
It's such a long journey, that's one year
就是那麼長路的時間,就是一年
that means
那個意思就是說
At that time, within a circle of the earth
那個時候地球繞一圈之內
it spins four hundred times
它轉了四百次
Now it can only go around three hundred and sixty-five times
現在繞一圈只能轉三百六十五次
this is what it means
這是這個意思
That is to say, the rotation was faster at that time
也就是說那時候轉得比較快
Quite a lot, about 10% faster
就快蠻多的,快了百分之十左右
so you can, this is another
所以你可以,這個又是一個
An evidence left to us by nature says
大自然留給我們的一個證據說
Look, the earth is turning slower and slower
你看嘛 地球越轉越慢嘛
it is true
是真的
this part
這個都 這個部分
Just now the physical reason
剛才那物理原因
The evidence left by this earth
這地球留下來的證據
It's the same thing
就是同一回事啊
let's see again
我們再來看看
Well, this is good, the earth is turning slower and slower
好 這個是好地球越轉越慢
of course say it again
當然再講一遍
You will never know in your life
你這一輩子你不會知道的
too little difference
差太少了
But this is not the end of the matter
可是這個事情不是這樣就結束了
You should know
你要知道啊
If the earth turns slower and slower
地球假如越轉越慢
If you ever read that physics mechanics
假如你曾經念過那個物理的力學的
you may remember
你還可能記得
There's a thing called conservation of foot momentum
有一個事情叫做腳動量守恆
this one thing it has
這個一個東西它有
There is a physical quantity called foot momentum
有一種 有一個物理量叫做腳動量
The bigger the momentum of the foot, the better the rotation
腳動量大它就轉得比較
The foot momentum is small and the rotation is slower
腳動量小就轉得比較慢
that thing
那個東西
that amount won't change
那個量不會變的
under the same circumstances
不變的情況之下
That is to say
也就是說
Why is the earth spinning
為什麼地球老在轉
this is another question
這是另外一個問題
students sometimes ask
學生有時候會問
Teacher, why does the earth rotate?
老師地球為什麼要轉
why does it keep turning
它為什麼老在轉
Actually the answer is very simple
其實答案很簡單
because it has so much foot momentum
因為它有這麼多腳動量
it can't be lost
它也丟不掉
it just has to turn every day
它就是只好天天轉
foot momentum is conservative
腳動量是守橫的
which means it won't increase
意思就是說它不會變多
will not become less
也不會變少
now there is a problem
那現在有問題
You say it turns slower and slower
你說它越轉越慢
less foot momentum
腳動量變少
You said that the foot momentum is not much
你就說腳動量不會多
not less
不會少
where did it go
那它跑哪去了
Where did the foot momentum go?
腳動量跑哪去了
this answer
這個答案
foot momentum has run away
腳動量有跑掉
where did you go
跑到哪去了呢
the answer is
答案是
Who told me to slow down
誰要我慢下來的
whoever has to take the momentum
誰就得把這腳動量拿去
who made me slow down
誰讓我慢下來的
moon
月亮
Pottery friction slows me down
陶系摩擦讓我慢下來
What about my angular momentum?
那我這些角動量呢
you have to mature you have to continue to take
你就得成熟你繼續得拿去
how to take it is to use
怎麼拿去的是用
Force drama, this is physics
用力劇啊這是物理的
what was the result
結果是怎麼樣
The earth is spinning slower and slower
地球越轉越慢沒錯
Angular momentum is getting less and less
角動量越來越少沒錯
That angular momentum is indestructible
那個角動量又不滅
The angular momentum of the arm went to the moon
手橫那個角動量跑到月球去了
what about the moon
那月球怎麼辦
That angular momentum is increasing
那角動量越來越多
As a result his reaction was
結果他的反應是
he has to turn faster
他必須要轉得要快一點
Or he was revolving to
或者是他公轉要
a little bigger
更範圍更大一點
his final reaction
最後他的反應
turn out
結果是
so
這樣
It's not wrong that he's still orbiting the earth
他還在繞地球沒有錯
But he goes farther and farther
但是他越繞越遠
sort of like a
有點像一個
go out like a spiral
像一個螺旋狀這樣繞出去
further and further
越來越遠
This one won't look too bad
這個也不會臉到多厲害
just slowly away
就是慢慢慢慢遠
how many
有多少呢
only so much a year
一年才這麼多
Click this much, about four centimeters, that's all.
點這麼多四公分左右就這樣
then this thing is true
那這個事情是真的
How dare I say it's true
我怎麼敢說是真的
Because our mountain was cold
因為我們那山涼過
look how cool
你看怎麼涼
this is awesome
這個好厲害
Is this the face?
這個是那張臉嘛
There are now 1 2 3 4 5 on this moon
這個月亮上現在有1 2 3 4 5
5 what have instruments placed on it
5個什麼有儀器放在上面
Because at that time the Apollo program had boarded six times
因為那時候阿波羅計畫有登過六次嘛
Put a lot of weird instruments on it every time
每次都放一大堆奇奇怪怪儀器在上面嘛
besides
還有
two
兩
There were other trips to the Soviet Union
還有其他次是蘇聯去的
No one in the Soviet Union has been there, yes
蘇聯沒有人去過沒錯
and unmanned lunar landers
還有無人的登月艇
logged in
登陸過
Also let go of the instrument
也放過儀器
There are a group of instrument people who look like this
有一批儀器人就長這個樣子
something like this
就差不多這樣一個東西
It is a special reflector
它是一種特別的反射鏡
It's a mirror, but it's the kind
就是鏡子 但是它是那種
at right angles to this
成直角的這種
called
叫做
Well, let's call it a reflector.
好吧 就叫反射鏡吧
What is this for? What are you doing over there?
這幹什麼 放在那邊幹什麼呢
are we from earth
是我們從地球上
wow this thing
哇 這個東西
If I accidentally swing someone else
我這樣不小心會揮到別人
do we have it from earth
我們從地球上就有嘛
made a big telescope
就做了很大的望遠鏡
the telescope probably
望遠鏡大概要
At least one meter in diameter
至少要一米以上口徑
be big enough
要夠大
just what
就什麼呢
Use a telescope to shoot lasers
用望遠鏡來發雷射
send laser
發雷射去
shot straight to the moon
一直射到月亮上去
Then there are reflectors on the moon
然後月亮上有反射鏡
it puts the mirror
它把反射鏡
That laser beam bounces back
那個雷射光就反射回來
This light, wow, hundreds of thousands of kilometers
這光 哇 幾十萬公里啊
send to receive back
發過去接收回來
that time
那個時候
The amount of reflection is already very weak, very weak
那個反射量都已經很微弱很微弱
this experiment is really bad
這實驗真不好
Do it well but do it successfully
做好做 但是做成功啊
what do you do
做什麼 這幹嘛幹嘛做這樣
you are the time back in time
你就是過去回來的時間
maybe a few seconds a few seconds
也許幾秒鐘 幾幾秒
that can be measured very precisely
那可以量得很精確
Divide the speed of light by two
成上光速 除以二
That's the distance
就是這個距離啊
You measure this year and measure next year
你今年量 明年再量
Measure it next year, measure it if you have nothing to do
後年再量 沒事就去量
measure ten years
量個十幾年
You find it's getting farther and farther away
你發現它越量真的越來越遠
Really, how much is it every year?
真的耶 每一年一點多少呢
almost that much
差不多就這麼多
Calculate this with us
這個跟我們算出來
The formula of foot momentum and hand scale is the same
用腳動量 手衡的公式算出來是一樣的
more and more far away from us
越量離我們越來越遠
Every year almost so much now
每一年差不多這麼多 現在
so what
那又怎麼樣呢
you can't see it, can you?
你也看不出來對不對
Did you see the volume getting smaller and smaller, no?
你有沒有看到越量越來越小 沒有嗎
That's actually very little
那實際上真的很少嘛
It seems that there is no need to worry, right?
好像不用擔心嘛對不對
not so good
沒那麼好事
Look at our earth now
你看我們地球現在這樣
what about 100 years ago
那100年前怎麼樣
100 years ago this became 100
100年前這個成100
All right
好吧
a little closer
稍微近這麼多嘛
Good 100 years I will give you 10,000 years
好100年我給你1萬年
OK
可以吧
Do you think 10,000 years is not enough to win?
1萬年你覺得不夠不夠贏嘛
I give you 1 million years
我給你1百萬年
Not enough for me to give you 100 million years
還不夠我給你1億年
The earth is very old, no problem
地球老得很啊沒有問題啊
You are not enough to win in 100 million years
你1億年你都不夠贏
I give you 1 billion years
我給你10億年
you go admit it
你去承認看
billions of years ago
幾十億年前
Wow
哇
where is the moon
月亮在哪裡啊
next to our earth
就在我們地球旁邊
what is it
是什麼事情啊
what does this mean
這什麼意思啊
What is the moon next to the earth
什麼叫做月亮就在地球旁邊
What does that mean
是什麼意思啊
this
這個
It's not about digestion
這不是當消化講
because it's true
因為這個事情是真的
very important one
很重要的一個
results of scientific research
科學研究的結果
research this thing
研究出這件事情
is the biggest look
是最大的樣子
The first person to study this phenomenon
第一個研究出這個現象的人
more than a hundred years ago
一百多年前
call darwin
叫達爾文
You say I know Darwin is the theory of evolution
你說我知道達爾文就是那個進化論
not him
不是他啦
is his son
是他兒子
His son's name is Darwin, of course.
他兒子當然也叫達爾文嘛
The man who evolved was Charles Darwin
那個進化那個人叫Charles Darwin
This astronomer's name is George Darwin
這個天文學家叫George Darwin
This is a famous astronomer
這是很有名的天文學家
This is what he came up with
這個都是他想出來的
and calculated
而且算出來的
We're all confirmed now
我們現在都證實啦
When he asked the question I just asked
他問到我剛才問的問題的時候呢
He boldly proposed a concept
他就很大膽的提出一個概念
What does it mean when the moon was next to the earth?
什麼叫做當時月亮就在地球旁邊
He said how the moon came
他說月亮是怎麼來的
It was thrown by the earth spinning too fast
是地球轉得太快甩出去的
that's ok
這樣可以吧
May I
可以嘛
And you also know that the rotation is fast at that time
而且你也知道那個時候轉得很快嘛
right
對不對
Then it got slower and slower
後來越來越慢的嘛
as soon as the situation
就像很快的情況之下
maybe in the event of some disturbance
也許有什麼擾動的情況下
the whole piece ran away
整塊就跑掉了
The one that got away is our current moon
那個跑掉的就是我們現在的月亮
what's wrong
有什麼不對
May I
可以嗎
When this theory was proposed more than 100 years ago
這個理論在100多年前提出的時候
immediately received a lot of attention
馬上就受到很大的關注
real
真的
Wow
哇
we understand now
我們現在懂了
and some even say
而且甚至還有人說
you run away a piece
你跑掉一塊
The earth must be missing a piece
那地球一定少掉一塊
So isn't there a big pull?
所以不是有個大的拔嗎
what is that pull
那個拔是什麼
ocean
海洋
It's too cold, isn't it?
太冰洋不就是嗎
look
你看
Wow
哇
this is great
這個太棒了
a theory like this
一個理論就這樣
The moon also understands
月亮也懂了
The ocean also understands
海洋也懂了
this is
這個是
it's a real thing
這真的事情
OK
OK
so at that time
所以在那個時候
growth of the moon
月亮的成長
This Kangying, this George Darwin proposed
這個康英這個 George Darwin 提出來的
It was proposed in 1878
1878年就提出來
This theory is nicknamed this
這個理論呢被這個就綽號吧
Parenthood theory
叫Parenthood theory
It's parent-child talk
就是親子說
It means that the moon is the descendant of our earth.
是說月亮是我們地球生出去的子孫這樣子
This is you see my picture is so big and only write this small piece
這是你看我這張這麼大只寫這一小塊
what is the reason
是什麼原因
Because there's something underneath, right?
因為底下還有東西嘛對不對
This is the theory number one of the birth of the moon
這個是月亮生成的理論一號
is there number two
那有二號嘛
This is number one what I just said
這是一號我剛剛講的
It's like going to World University, right?
好像投入世大對不對
Of course, some people think it's impossible.
當然也有人覺得不太不太可能啊
but this
而是這樣啦
not like that
不是那樣啦
it was then
是當時就是
When you formed, when the solar system formed, large and small gathered
你形成的時候太陽系形成的時候大大小小就聚集
I gather here
我這邊聚一塊
Are you the moon or the earth?
你是月亮還是地球就這樣
it's also a theory
這也是一個理論
there's nothing wrong with that
這也沒什麼不對
This is called, nicknamed "Siblings"
這個叫做 綽號叫做手足說
called sisterhood
叫做 sisterhood
There's another piece over here
那這邊還有一塊
It's theory number two and number three.
就是理論二號還有三號
number three is
三號是
it's all modern
這都是近代的
This was a hundred years ago, more than a hundred years ago
這都要一百年前 百多年前
This is what the spouse said
這是spouse的說法
spouse said
配偶說
what is it then
是什麼呢
just look at it
看一下就知道
was captured
是捕捉來的
That is to say, our earth was a
就是說我們地球當時是個
bachelor
光棍
I am professional
就是我自己在專業
what year
那哪一年
it's all about
這都是講
Early days of the solar system, infancy
太陽系早期 嬰兒期的時候的事情
There won't be such a big change later
後來不會有這麼大的變動
We accidentally walked a guy nearby
我們不小心附近走過一個家伙
is the moon
是月亮
got sucked into the earth
就被地球吸住了
It's okay if there's nothing wrong with it
那有什麼不行也可以嘛
This is theory number three
這是理論三號
Every theory it supports what it says
每一種理論它要支援其說的話
must be right in school
必須在立學上要對
It's also possible that it's too impossible
還有可能性要太不可能也不行
But you just say
但是你只要譬如說
pei says
佩偶說
We now think Mars has two small moons
我們現在就認為火星有兩個小月亮
I just had a photo
就我剛才有一個照片
That's how the two little moons were caught just now
剛剛那兩個小月亮就是這樣抓來的
So this is not to say nonsense.
所以這個也不是說無中生有亂講
it's really possible
這真的有可能
Is it possible in school
在立學上是不是可能
Plus
再加上
At the time of this Lantern Moon
當初這個燈月的時候
Every time some rocks come back
每一次都有安一些石頭回來
rocks of the moon moved back
月亮的岩石搬回來
Then draw in the laboratory
然後實驗室裡面畫驗
compared with the earth
跟地球的來比較
It's basically the same as the rocks of the earth.
基本上跟地球的岩石差不多啦
But there's always something a little different
但是總有多少有點不一樣
those little ones are different
那些小少的不一樣
Can you use any of these theories to explain
你可不可以用這些哪一個理論來解釋
The result is almost
結果是差不多
Every theory seems to be right
每一個理論都有好像很對的地方
There are also flaws
也有缺陷的地方
Then we can't argue, right?
那就爭論不下對不對
Then we will write these three here now
那我們現在就把這三個寫在這邊
You can also be your judge
你也可以做你的判斷
whichever one you like, right?
你就喜歡哪一個對不對
we wait for you to reveal
我們等你會揭曉嗎
because we now only think
因為我們現在只認為
It can't be all right, right?
這不可能都對嘛對不對
then you can now
那你現在就可以
You are the only one like this
你自己就獨哪一個這樣的
Then I will tell you the answer now
那我現在就把答案跟大家講
the answer is
答案是
none of above
以上皆非
We now think the answer is
我們現在認為答案是這樣
it came out
是撞出來了
Where did it come from?
越讓哪來的
knocked out
撞出來了
what is knocked out
什麼叫撞出來了
this is still
這個還是
this is not a photo
這不是照片啊
This is of course human
這當然是人話
This is also the infancy of the solar system
這個是也是太陽系的嬰兒期
That is, within the first 100 million years of 4.6 billion years ago
就是說46億年前的頭1億年之內吧
Isn't it infancy?
不是嬰兒期嘛
something that happened at that time
那時候發生的某一件事情
what does it look like
看起來有點像什麼呢
It was at that time that things were still not in order
是那個時候東西還秩序還沒有定
It's just that the solar system is not messed up
就是太陽系沒亂七八糟
everyone has everyone's track
大家有大家的軌道
But it hasn't been cleaned yet.
可是都還沒有清理乾淨那個意思
once the earth collided with another guy
有一次地球跟另外一個傢伙撞到了
that guy is big enough
那個傢伙夠大
If the earth is so big
假地球這麼大的話
That guy probably
那個傢伙大概估計吧
he is so big
他有這麼大
Mars is big enough
火星這麼大夠大
These two things collided
這兩個東西撞到一起去了
Of course it's not the same when we bump into each other
撞到一起當然非同小隔
hit it hard
撞下去不得了
The whole thing just hits everything into ashes
整個就撞所有的什麼灰飛煙滅
This bomb is everywhere
到處滿天都是這個炸
something knocked out
撞出來的東西
Most of the things crashed out and flew all over the sky
大部分的東西撞出來滿天飛
Big back and sucked back
大回來又被吸回來
right? drop back again
對不對 又降回來
still something to get
還有一些東西得到
Accidentally get more energy
不小心得到更多的能量
run away, run away forever
就跑掉了 就永遠跑掉了
there are many things
還有很多東西呢
Didn't run away, didn't fall down
也沒跑掉 也沒掉下來
it had to go around
它只好繞
because it also has foot momentum
因為它也有腳動量
If you have feet, you have to go around
有腳用量就得繞
It is likely that the earth at that time
很可能地球那個時候
There is a ring
有一個一環帶的
All are the fastest substances
全部都是最快物質
like what it is now
就像現在的什麼形
rage star is like this
怒星就是這樣
not saturn
不是土星
Doesn't Saturn have rings?
土星不是有個環嗎
I guess the earth was like that at that time
估計那個時候地球就那個樣
Then what
然後呢
inside the rings of saturn
在土星環裡面
these big and small things
這些大大小小的東西
It has this gravitational force in it
它中間都有這個萬有引力
slowly inhale
慢慢慢慢在吸
Doesn't it like to be round in the end?
到後來它不是很喜歡變圓嗎
yes big enough
對啊 夠大
If it is round enough, it will become the moon, that's not how it came about
就夠圓了,就變成月亮了,不是這樣來的
Is this theory over?
這個理論是不是就這樣講講就過了
People say it's right, right, right, right?
就人家說對了對了對了,不會嘛
You want to prove it, how can such a person prove it?
你要證實嘛,這種人怎麼證實啊?
It's right for you to talk nonsense like this.
你這樣子亂講一個就對了啊
But this is not nonsense now, it has been proven to be broken
但是這個現在不是亂講,就被證實破
How was it confirmed?
怎麼證實的呢?
confirmed in the computer
在電腦裡面證實
this was ten years ago
這在十幾年前
There are scientists who use computers
有科學家就利用電腦的
The computer is getting bigger and bigger, the ability, this ability
電腦越做越大,能力,這個能力
more and more powerful
功力越來越強
I am not me, I say scientists
我就不是我啦,我說科學家就把
such a crash event
這樣的一個撞擊事件
Simulate, use a computer to simulate
模擬,就用電腦去模擬
Mock doesn't tell him to call someone to draw Kao Dong Tu
模擬不叫他叫一個人來畫考東圖
Then draw it like this
然後畫出來就這樣
No, let him do the math
不是啊 讓他去算
He must base his calculations on
他算的時候都必須要根據
correct physics
對的物理原理去算
because it's not easy
因為不好算
All relevant physical aspects of such events
所有有關這種事件有相關的物理的
All truths must be written in mathematical formulas
道理全部都要寫成數學公式
Then give him a two thing and start him banging
然後給他一個兩個東西開始讓他撞
After hitting it, it will become like this
撞到後來會變成這樣
then what happens
然後會變成怎麼樣
Look at the last in the computer
看看最後在電腦裡面
Is it possible to create a moon
可不可以製造出一個月球來
this thing worked
這個事情成功了
Since it was successful
既然成功了
Is there anyone going to steal something?
有沒有人去偷改什麼東西
really can be successful
真的可以成功
So the theory is accepted
所以這個理論就被接受了
This theory was accepted
這個理論被接受了
as we now think
也就像我們現在認為
That's how the moon came about
月球就是這樣來的
that's how it came out
是這樣撞出來的
Of course, there are many other problems derived from this.
這裡面當然又有很多衍生的其他問題
For example, maybe you see this and you think
譬如說也許你看到這個你就想
Yes, that Jupiter
對啊那個木星
Isn't Saturn just like this now?
土星不就現在不就這個樣嗎
Then you can ask the next sentence saying
然後你可以問下一句話說
those Saturn things
那土星的那些東西
Instead, why didn't it grow into a moon?
反而怎麼沒有長成月亮
why not
為什麼沒有
Why can the earth grow into the moon
為什麼地球就可以長成月亮
I know this too
這個也是知道的
know why
知道為什麼
Because Saturn is bigger
因為土星到底比較大
that gravity is very strong
那個重力很強很強
the substance near it
它那個附近的那個物質
want to attract each other
想要變成互相吸
want to be the moon
想要變成月亮
It cannot be done in the process of a proto-moon
它一個原月亮的過程當中是做不到的
Because the tidal force is too strong
因為潮汐力太強了
If you want to mess with that layer, I'll tear it up
你想弄那一層就給你扯碎
tidal force will tear it apart
潮汐力就會把它扯碎
so it doesn't fit
所以它合不起來
I know this too
這個也是知道的
the earth is so small
那地球這麼小
The tidal force is not so fierce
那個潮汐力沒有這麼兇悍
it is possible to grow a moon
它是可以長出一個月亮
this is also possible
這也是可以的
what about this theory
這個理論呢
by the way
還順便的
some get some unexpected benefits
有一些得到一些意外的好處
For example, I just said
譬如說我剛剛講說
stones you brought from karma
你從業量拿來的石頭
i'll say something
我會花言一下
How is it different from the earth
跟地球有什麼不一樣
then use this theory
那用這個理論
Can you explain those differences?
是不是可以解釋那些不一樣呢
it's not my specialty
這不是我的專長
but the answer is yes
但是答案是可以
there are some interesting
還有一些有趣
conscious
有意識的
for example by-products
譬如說副產品
Here I will tell one of them is very interesting
這裡我講其中有一個很有趣
this thing is like this
這個事情是這樣
This is in our solar system
這個是我們太陽系裡面的
I say the tuba members of the family
我說家族的大號的成員
This size is the proportion is correct
這個大小就是比例是對的
If the earth is so big
假如地球這麼大的話
There are four older than us
比我們大的有四個
Just the four outside
就外面這四個
the outer four
最外面的四個
The biggest is of course Jupiter
最大的當然是木星
then saturn
然後是土星
Uranus Kaiwang
天王星 凱王星
There is also a name that was removed from the list a few years ago
還有一個前幾年被除名的名字
The heart is small, don't worry about it
心很小,不要理它
The earth is actually only this big
地球其實只有這麼大
look at this
你看一下這個
this is our planet
這是我們的行星
this is ours
這是我們的
this is still our planet
這還是我們的行星
This is us, this is what's inside us
這是我們啦,這個是我們裡面的
One is Jingxing
一顆叫就是精星
about the same size , a little bit smaller than us
差不多大,比我們小一點點
It doesn't matter, the living star is just that big
這不管啦,活星就是這麼大而已
these are all the moons
這些是所有的月亮
bigger moon
比較大號的月亮
How big is that small moon?
那小號的月亮一大多呀
There are hundreds of them
一大多呀,上百個都有
this is big
這個是大
a whole bunch of these planets
一大堆這些行星的
family of the moon
月亮的家族
members line up
成員排起來
from largest to second largest
從最大的,第二大
the moon is here
月球在這裡
this one
這一個
these four
這四個
is famous
是滿有名的
called galilean moon
叫加利略月亮
It's all about Jupiter
這都是木星的
Galileo
就是四百年間加利略
not binoculars
不是把望眼鏡
time to see it ? also see jupiter
去看的時候嗎?還要看木星
As a result, I saw four moons, these four
結果看到四個月亮就這四個
is large
是大號的
OK look
OK 你看喔
The moon, all the moons line up like this
月亮 所有的月亮排起來就是這樣
our moon is really big
我們的月亮真的很大
Although not the biggest
雖然不是最大了
but it's really big
可是真的很大
how about this
這個怎麼樣呢?
look back
你回頭看一下
so big
人家這麼大
its the moon
它的月亮才這樣
we do
我們這樣
our moon
我們的月亮
How did we get such a big moon
我們何得何能有這麼大的月亮
our moon is really big
我們的月亮真的很大
I kid you not
我不騙你
in the end is
到底是
This has always been a problem
這個也是一直都是一個問題
Astronomers have been asking this question too
天文學家也一直在問這個問題
Why is our moon so big?
說我們的月亮為什麼這麼大呢?
have no idea
不知道
Now
現在
Now is this a problem? How big does it grow?
現在這有問題嗎? 它種出來多大?
How old is it?
就多大嗎
it can even be
它甚至還可以是
The one bigger than our earth is fine.
比我們地球還大的那一個都可以嘛
that is to say we are now
就是說我們現在
we live on the small one
我們住在那個小的那個上面嘛
those hearts
那些心啊
why does it have to be so much smaller than you
為什麼它還必須要比你小很多
No one stipulated this
沒有人規定這樣嘛
Whatever happens when it hits
撞出來是怎麼樣就怎麼樣
it's big or small
這可大可小
So what if it's quite big now?
那現在是蠻大的就怎麼樣
no problem, right?
沒有問題嘛 對不對
Ok, this problem is also solved
好 這個問題也解決了
I believe this question is for us
這問題我相信對我們來講
In fact, very few people actually ask this question.
其實很少人真的問過這個問題嘛
right
對不對
Because we have long been used to our moon
因為我們早就習慣我們月亮
I thought the moon in the world should be this big
以為天下的月亮都應該這麼大
No la
沒有啦
OK
OK
Another astronomer or physicist
再一個這個天文學家或者物理學家
Anyway, the puzzling thing is this
反正百思不得其解的事情是這個
You see, the earth is placed like this
你看這個地球是這樣的擺的
then you call
之後你電
So you buy it back and buy it like this
所以你買回來就這樣買
It's not that you shake it when you buy it.
不是買回來就搖了
It's like this when I bought it.
買回來就是這樣斜的啦
I didn't move it
不是被我搬的啦
right
對不對
We all... all one-ball hawks do this, right?
我們都...所有的一球鷹都這樣擺的對不對
Why
為什麼
Doesn't it look good?
這樣好看嗎 不是啦
it's slanted
它就是斜的嘛
What is it oblique to?
它相對於什麼東西斜啊
that's right
是這樣的啊
Then we now call it yellow rice noodles
然後我們現在這個是叫做黃稻麵
is the sun
就是太陽
we know which side of the sun
我們知道太陽那個面
If the face is flat
是那個面是平的話
Our earth actually rotates in Y direction
我們地球其實是Y的轉的
Then there's an angle here, right?
那這裡有個角度嘛 對不對
This is called the inclination of the Earth's rotation.
這個就叫地球自轉的傾角
The angle of 23 and a half degrees
23度半那個角度啊
It is because of this angle that 4G is available, right?
也就是因為有這個角度才有4G啊什麼對不對
think about it
你想想看
If it turns like this
假如它是這樣轉的啊
until the sun turns like this
到太陽這樣轉
There is no 4G here
這沒有4G啦
4G too
4G也是
We figured it out after we knew there were these things
我們知道有這些事情以後才想通了
Yes, that's right
對喔 這樣喔
That's how it came
也就是這樣來的嘛
why is it so crooked
為什麼會這樣歪
because of you because
因為你因為
According to the theory of our solar system formation
按照我們的太陽系生成的理論來講
is generated like this
是這樣生成的
4.6 billion years ago
是46億年前
a big pot
一團大盆盆
a lot of little things
一大堆小小的一大堆東西
everyone is here
大家都在
everyone is going around
大家都在繞
everyone is turning
大家都在轉
why turn
為什麼要轉
because when it is generated
因為它生成的時候
accidentally assigned a lot of angular momentum
不小心分到很多角動量
what about it
它怎麼辦
had to go around
只好繞
just turn
就轉
when turning
轉的時候
under gravity
在重力的情況之下
This is how my tour is already
自己的環遊已經是這樣
The most stable condition is a flat turn
最穩定的狀況是一個扁的轉
a disc turn
一個盤狀的轉
So the early solar system
所以早期的太陽系
It's such a big pile of material
就是這樣一大堆物質的
another plate
再轉的一個盤子狀
These things start with each other
這些東西互相就開始
It starts to generate planets due to spiritual power
它由於靈力就開始生成行星
little parade what moon
小遊行什麼月亮
so formed
就這樣形成了
you pay attention when forming
形成的時候你注意
Every thing that forms is assigned some angle measure
每一個形成的東西都分到一些角度量
it's going to turn like this
它都是要這樣轉的
so these planets
所以這些行星
on this face
在這個面上
Everything turns like this
通通都是這樣轉的
This is how the revolution works
公轉都是這樣
small circle like this
小圈的這樣
big circle like this
大圈的這樣
Anyway, it's like this
反正都是這樣轉
It rotates like this
它自轉也是這樣轉
also in the same direction
也是同一個方向
Because it's divided into such an angular measure
因為它分到這麼有角度量
what about it
它怎麼辦
it just gets better
它就只好轉
Just this sentence
就這句話
so it turns like this
所以都是這樣轉
That's a straight turn
那這樣就是直直的轉
Why is it crooked?
為什麼歪掉了呢
why is it crooked
為什麼會歪掉
Whether it will be crooked or not
無論會不會歪掉的
Because the angle it is assigned is a small vector
因為它分到的角度量是一個小的向量
It's really the angle
真的是這樣的角度量
It's all written down now
都總現在寫掉了
It's pretty well written.
這寫的還蠻厲害的
this has always been a problem
這個一直是問題
so why
所以為什麼
will slant off
會斜掉
Then you look at other planets found
那你看其他行星發現
Mars is crooked too
火星也是歪的
Mars is about the same as us
火星跟我們差不多
Still more than 20 degrees crooked
還有歪二十幾度
Well
呃
other planets
其他行星
less crooked
比較不歪
there is an even stranger
有一個更奇怪的
In fact, it is careful
其實就是精心
it's not crooked
它沒有歪
But it turns like this
可是它是這樣轉的
turn instead
反而轉的
it turns very slowly
它轉得很慢
but the opposite
但是是反的
it's even weirder
這更奇怪了
I don't know why
這也不知道為什麼
It can't be reversed.
它不可能是反的轉的啊
That is to say, you carefully
也就是說你在精心上
The sun comes out from the west
太陽是打西邊出來的啊
real
真的
That is to say, these rotations of these planets
那就是說這些行星的這些轉
Why is it so strange
為什麼會奇奇怪怪這樣
The simplest is why our earth is so crooked
最簡單的是我們地球為什麼會這麼歪掉啊
Well, it seems that I can answer it now.
那現在也有好像也可以解答囉
It's just crooked
就是撞歪了嘛
Didn't you get hit before?
當初不是被撞過嗎
hit it
撞了就是
If the shoe is bumped, it will be crooked.
結鞋撞的就歪掉了嘛
that's all
就這樣
how big is that
那有多大的一個東西
what a powerful one
多強大的一個
How can this collider bend so much?
這個撞機才能夠歪這麼多呢
It seems that this thing is not working
好像這個事還不行
this is not enough
這樣子還不夠
possibly earlier
可能更早期
when there is a larger combination
有更大的組合的時候
Big and small
大小撞的
It's crooked when it's messed up
亂七八糟的時候就已經歪掉了
that other
那其他的
The core can also be explained like this
核心也可以這麼解釋
Why does carefulness reverse
精心為什麼會反掉
obviously got hit
顯然是被撞的
reverse
反掉
Will it be reversed?
會不會撞反呢
that's all
就這樣
this is all
這個都是
ever-great problem
一向以來的極大的問題
But now we put this
可是現在我們把這個
big collider this
大撞機這個
concept brought in
概念帶進去
seems to be able to explain
好像都可以解釋
OK, this is what we are talking about about the moon
OK這個是我們講月亮的
deep
深層
we again
我們再次
It also announced and advertised some human exploration of the moon
又預告做廣告說了一些人類對月亮的探索
also a story
也是故事
we tell stories like this
我們講這樣的故事
What I just said has nothing to do with people
剛才講的跟人一點關係都沒有
Except those recorded at the time of the date
除了日權時有記錄那些
Everything else is natural
其他都就是自然性
It's just that people have a special love for the moon
就是人對月亮當然情有獨中
did a lot of things
幹了不少事情
This story can be told from 1958 to 1957
這個故事可以從1958年1957年講起
this day october 4th
這一天10月4號
It's the day humans enter the space age
是人類進入太空時代的那一天
what happened
發生了什麼事呢
the Soviet Union
這個蘇聯
this country no longer exists
這個國家已經不存在了
The Soviet Union launched an artificial miniature
蘇聯當天那一天發射了一個人造微型
into orbit
進入軌道
this is a big deal
這個事情很大條
because it's too hard
因為太難做到
Now we find it easy to do
現在我們覺得很容易做到
it's really hard to do
這實在是非常難做到
This is the first round in the middle of the cold war
這是冷戰中間的第一回合
It's the camp of the Soviet Union
就蘇聯大大的營了
he was the first to enter the orbit of a satellite
他第一個進入人造衛星的軌道
first his artificial satellite into orbit
第一個他的人造衛星進入軌道
Satellite called Sparknik 1
衛星叫Sparknik 1
This is a photo of a replica
這是一個複製品的照片
not so big
沒有這麼大
probably only this big
大概只有這麼大
this is rough
這個很粗糙
You look like a child's toy now
你現在看起來像兒童玩具一樣
He went into orbit and did nothing
他進入軌道也沒幹什麼
It is to play the signal BVV of a tape recorder
就是放一個錄音機的訊號BVV
That's it
就是這樣
The ground received that signal
地面就接到那個訊號
Wow, this is a great progress for mankind
哇 這個是人類的一大進步
great advance in civilization
文明的一大進步
just at that moment
就那一瞬間
This is humanity entering the space age
這個是人類進入太空時代
the back of this
這個中後面的
lots of questions to ask
可以問的問題很多
soviet won
蘇聯贏了
This fact is
這個道理其實
is history
就是歷史
Simply put
簡單來講就是
that time
那個時候
want to enter satellite
想要進入人造衛星
to get into orbit
要進入軌道
you must have powerful rockets
你必須要有強大的火箭
Where was the mighty rocket at that time
那個時候強大的火箭在哪裡呢
in Germany
在德國
How can there be in Germany?
德國怎麼會有呢
because he fought
因為他打仗
When he developed during the 20th World War
二十大戰的時候他發展的時候
Called the V2 rocket
叫V2火箭
I don't know the detailed story here.
這個詳細故事我就這邊不會
not too detailed
不講太詳細
this is a big war
這個是大戰
at the end
尾聲的時候
used by germany to bomb london
德國用來轟炸倫敦用的
Britain was bombed badly
英國被炸得很慘
But soon the war will be over
可是很快大戰就結束了
when it's over
結束的時候呢
within a few months
那幾個月之內呢
cold war has begun
冷戰已經開始了
the first to enter berlin
先進入柏林的是
soviet red army
蘇聯的紅軍
Once the Soviet Union entered the Red Army and entered Germany,
蘇聯一進入紅軍進入德國以後
all good things
好東西全部
Already spotted
早就看準了
block all
全部封鎖
move all back to germany
全部搬回德國
Go to the Soviet Union, the rocket power is the most important one
蘇聯去 火箭機力是其中最重要的一個
personnel data equipment
他把人員資料設備
All the knowledge is packaged and sent back to the Soviet Union
所有的知識全部打包送回蘇聯去
So later, it entered the humane world and was already in orbit.
所以後來先進入人道已經軌道用
This rocket won't work. It's too small. It needs to be bigger and bigger.
這個火箭不行 這還太小 還要更大更大
But no matter what, the Soviet Union has this advantage
但不管怎麼樣 蘇聯就是有得到這個優勢
first in orbit
先進入軌道
This is the first round of the Cold War, the Soviet Union has already won
這個是冷戰的第一回合 蘇聯是已贏了
America lost, but not too much
美國輸啊 可是也沒有輸太多
Because you see this January of the second year
因為你看 這個第二年的1月
America also succeeded
美國也成功了 美國後面幹嘛
Also successfully launched his first artificial satellite
也成功了發射他的第一個人造衛星
this photo is very famous
這張照片是很有名的
A photo of a celebration dinner at the White House
一張在白宮慶功宴的一張照片
this is not a rocket
這個這不是火箭
rocket big big big big
火箭很大很大很大
This is the artificial satellite on top of the rocket
這是火箭頂端放的那個人造衛星
This is what artificial satellites look like
人造衛星就長這個樣
there is an instrument inside
裡面有個儀器
It is the instrument used by this professor
是這個教授的放的儀器
It's called Van Allen
這叫做Van Allen
Have any students heard
有沒有同學有沒有聽過
Pan Allan radiation belts outside the Earth
泛艾倫輻射帶在地球外面
It's made in his laboratory
就是他的實驗室做出來
of these three
這三個人裡面
This was an official at the time
這個是當時的一個官員
officials no one will remember
官員沒有人會記得的
scientists remember
科學家有記得
This guy is a legend
這個家伙就是很傳奇的人物了
His name is Wander von Braun
他叫Wander von Braun
got the name
得過名字
who is it
是誰呢
is the lead scientist of the V2 rocket.
是V2火箭的主持科學家
big boss of v2 rocket
V2火箭的大老闆
He was never packed back by the Soviet Union
他總而沒有被蘇聯打包回去呢
This is his later
這個是他後來的
write in the field like this
字段裡面這樣寫
I have always hated the Communist Party
一向就很討厭共產黨
When the Red Army came in
那紅軍進來的時候
He hid in the box
他就躲到箱下去了
Does he know the Nazi king?
他知道納粹王了嘛
he hides first
他就先躲起來
In a few months, the U.S. military will come
過幾個月美軍來了
he ran out
他就跑出來
Hey, I'm here, I'm like this
欸 我在這裡喔 我這樣
America is like Huo Zhibao
美國簡直是如霍治寶啊
It's not like Huo Zhibao, it's the real Huo Zhibao
不是如霍治寶 是真的霍治寶
just hurry him up
就趕快把他
Li Yu's please come to the United States to do a bigger cause
李玉的請到美國去做更大的事業
That business is called NASA
那個事業叫做NASA
Is it early NASA
是不是NASA早期的
when it was founded
創立的時候的
Can't say the biggest
不能說最大啦
Largest Engineering in Science
在科學方面最大的工程
Actually, think about this
這個其實你想一下對這個
history is weird
歷史很吊詭啦
he was a nazi
他是納粹黨員
And a high-ranking Nazi
而且是高級的納粹黨員
His companions were put to death
他有同伴同仁被處死
are war criminals
都是戰犯
Either shot or hanged
不是槍斃就是上吊死
Not only was he not judged
他不但沒有受到審判
It is also very reasonable to invite to the United States to do a bigger cause
也非常理喻地請到美國去做更大的事業
look how happy he is
你看他多高興
Do you have
有沒有
This is tantamount to saying that he led the first success here
這個就是等於說他帶領了第一個成功在這裡
NASA was established at the end of 1958
這個1958年年底的時候NASA就成立了
The United States felt that we lost the first round
美國就覺得說我們第一回合輸了
extremely straight up
極其直追吧
We will use the power of the whole country
我們要用全國的力量
Founded NASA
成立了NASA
The United States lost the second round
第二回合美國又輸了
The second round is to send people to orbit
第二回合是把人送上軌道
or the Soviet Union
還是蘇聯先
The third round is even bigger. Who landed on the moon?
第三回合更大條了是誰登陸月球
can go back to the story we tell about the moon
可以回到我們講月球的故事
In the third round, both sides watched helplessly to see who would win.
第三回合兩邊都眼睜睜的看誰贏
That's not something that can be done every day
那不是三天兩頭可以做到
who sent a man to the moon first
誰先把人送到月球去
This is history, you know
這個就變歷史了你知道
1969 US Apollo 1
1969年美國阿波羅斯一號
crashed the moon
就崩潰了月球
mr armstrong like go down there
阿姆士壯先生就像走下去有沒有
That's one small step for me, one giant leap for mankind
我的一小步就是人類的一大步一樣
that's the story
那就是那個故事
The United States has been to the United States seven times in a row
美國就連續的去了七次
succeeded six times
成功了六次
The USSR failed once
蘇聯一次都沒成功
But he has logged in without anyone
可是他沒有人的也有登陸
It's a success
也算滿成功了
But if you lose, you lose
可是輸了就是輸了嘛
Don't say that you seem to lose half, there is no such thing
你不要說你好像輸一半沒有這樣的事情嘛
you just lost
你就是輸了嘛
In 1972
1972年的時候
Well
呃
both sides shouted stop
兩邊都喊停了
don't go
不要去了
The reason is very simple
道理很簡單
Aren't we running the 100 meters to see who wins?
我們不是在跑百米看誰贏嗎
Have you ever seen someone running a 100 meters and still running?
你有沒有看過誰跑百米跑完還在跑的啊
no
沒有嘛
run until then
跑到那時候
Win or lose is clear
輸贏很清楚了嘛
Even if you win, you don't want to run away.
贏的也不想跑了嘛
If you lose, you don't even want to run away.
輸的更不想跑了嘛
The United States just doesn't want to run away.
那美國這方面就是不想跑了
America really can't run
真的是美國跑不動了
It's a waste of national power
實在是國力消耗太厲害
It's not easy to do this kind of thing
做這種事情不是簡單
this is very scary
這是非常恐怖的
At that time it was still fighting in Vietnam
那個時候還在打越戰
The two ends burn like this
這個兩頭燒這樣
Even though the country has put in all the power of Maoism to do it
國家就雖然拼足毛主義力氣做到了
But after doing it, it's really like running a hundred meters
可是做到以後真的像跑百米一樣
worn out
累死了
I'm exhausted. Don't do it anymore.
累死了不要再做了
leave this one
這個就留下一個
We have been to the moon such a record
我們去過月球這樣一個紀錄
yes
沒錯
then want to ask
然後想要問說
why are we going to the moon
我們為什麼要去月球
I tell you no one can tell
我跟你講沒有人講得出來
you see everything as if
你看什麼都好像覺得
Going to the moon is so amazing
去月球多了不起多了不起
It's just to see who wins
其實背後只是在看誰贏而已
Just run 100 meters
就是跑百米啦
you really outperformed you are really amazing
你真的跑贏你真的很了不起啦
But do you want to ask that question
但是你要不要問那個問題說
why should i run
我為什麼要去跑
just want to win
就是想贏嘛
What about winning?
那贏了就怎麼樣呢
How are you doing?
你沒怎麼樣啊
It's human psychology like this
這是人類的心理這樣
So what role does the moon play in this matter?
那月球在這件事情扮演什麼角色呢
It's just that I was taken as a goal by you to fight for this
就是我是被你們當作什麼目標來爭取這樣
How much science is really done?
真的有做到多少科學呢
a little bit
有一點啦
For example, didn't you use the reflection technique just now?
譬如說剛才不是用了反射技嗎
just now
剛才還有沒有
And this one from Lantern Moon
還有燈月的這個
I'll show you the back of my side first.
我先我這邊到底後面給你們看一下
Really some achievements
真的有一些成就啦
brought back some stones
又拿了一些石頭回來
It can be analyzed that's right
可以分析這沒錯
And there is an earthquake chair left on it
還有還留了地震椅在上面
It's not an earthquake, it's a moonquake.
還量到不是地震 月震喔
Really very few
真的有 很少啦
Tiny really has moonquakes
小小的真的有月震喔
Isn't the moon dead?
月亮不是死死的嗎
How could it shake?
怎麼會震呢
This can also be studied
這也可以研究
Guess it's because of the tide
猜想是因為潮汐的
caused by the earth to its tides
地球給它的潮汐造成的
This is a scientific achievement
這個都算是科學成就
but you have to think about it
但是你要想想看
How much effort was spent to follow the mining force, material resources, time, and manpower?
花了多大的力量跟採力、物力、時間、人力下去
to do this? certainly not worth it
才做到這一點嗎?當然不值得
so i secretly tell you
所以我偷偷跟你們講
Daoyeqiu is not for science or human progress
刀業求不是為了科學或人類的什麼進步
It's a cold war to see who wins
是冷戰要看誰贏
By the way did a little science
順便做了一點科學
so
這樣
So is science worth spending so much money on?
那科學這一點科學值得花這麼多錢去做嗎?
It's not worth it for us who do science
對我們做科學的人來講說不值得
But he didn't say he wants to do science
但是他沒有說他要做科學
is in the international
就是在國際上
He wants to be the leader. He's the big brother of the western camp.
他要當領導他是西方陣營的老大哥
he will do these things
他就要做這些事
right
對不對
what's right or wrong? it's your judgment
什麼對錯?這是你的判斷
OK, there are some behind this
OK 那這個後面有一些
I can tell you a fun story later
待會可以跟大家再當好玩故事講的
But let's go back to what we were talking about
但是我們要回到剛才講的事情
What did you say just now? It hasn't been resolved yet.
剛才講什麼事情 到現在還沒解決
Why is the moon so wet for me
月亮為什麼這麼點潮的我
not yet
還沒講到
In fact, this truth has just been explained through the earth.
這個道理其實剛才已經透過地球來講過
Isn't our earth being turned slower and slower by its tides?
我們地球不是被它潮汐的越轉越慢嗎
you turn around
你反過來看
The earth has tides on it, what's more powerful
地球對它有潮汐 還更厲害嘛
the earth is so big
地球這麼大
it's small
它小小的
our tidal influence on it
我們對它的潮汐影響
although it has no ocean
雖然它沒有海洋
But tides don't have to be in the water to happen
但是潮汐並不一定在水裡才發生
It deserves the same friction as the ground. Squeeze what.
它都應得地底下一樣有摩擦 擠啊什麼
still the same friction
還是一樣 會有摩擦
we are so big it is so small
我們這麼大 它這麼小
We have a big influence on its tides
我們對它的潮汐影響很大
we'll make it spin slower and slower
我們會讓它越轉越慢
real
真的
What, how strong is it?
什麼 強到什麼程度呢
it stopped turning
它早就不轉了
This can't be called
這個就叫不轉了
It can't be the lowest energy
不能再能量最低就這樣
it can't turn anymore
它不能再更不轉
It's called non-rotation
它這樣子就叫做不轉
The truth is the same
道理就是一樣
Our friction with it
我們對它的吵析摩擦
It's long gone
早就不轉了啦
not now
不是現在還不轉啦
Don't say that it stopped turning dozens of years ago.
不要幾十一年前它就不轉了啦
so this is not a coincidence
所以這個不是巧合嘛
it is
它就是
You can say it's exhausted
你可以說它沒力氣了
All the strength has been worn away by you
所有力氣都被你磨光了
that's all
就只剩這樣啦
so it's no coincidence
所以這不是巧合
So other angry stars and picture stars
所以其它的怒星、圖星
Its moons are all like this
它的月亮通通都是這樣
I don't know it stopped turning decades ago.
不知道幾十一年前就已經不轉了
that's all
就這樣
this is the answer to
這個就是回答到
We just started with that question
我們剛才起先那個問題啦
should be by now
到現在應該
many questions just asked
很多剛才問到的問題
already understood
都已經有了解了
ok now we can
好 現在我們就可以
So back to a story we told at the end
所以回到最後我們講的一個故事
This is the rocket that was used when the Apollo program was launched
這個是當初發射阿波羅計畫的時候就用這種火箭
This rocket is called the Saturn V
這個火箭叫做土星五號Saturn V
really big enough
真的夠大喔
This is the largest rocket ever made by mankind
這個是人類目前到現在做的最大的火箭
Not this one, this series needs one every time
不是這一個這個系列每一次就要一個
so big
大到這個樣子
When I got to that Washington, that's when I served there.
我到那個華盛頓就是那時候我在那邊服務的時候
Every time I go to the US capital horse space museum
每次就跑到美國首都馬太空博物館
All the NASA babes go in later
所有NASA的寶貝後來就全部進去
great size
太棒規模又大
it has a show want to show this thing
它有一個展聽想要展示這個東西
At least show you how big this tail is
至少把這個尾巴給你看有多大
right
對不對
To let you know wow, going to the moon was scary
讓你瞭解 哇 當初去登月時還是恐怖
how big is it
那它有多大一間
It's too big, so there's no way to exhibit it
太大了 這沒辦法展覽嘛
very smart it looks like this
很聰明啊 它這樣子
it uses a model
它用一用模型
Just made such a small block
只用做了這樣一個小塊
then use the mirror
然後用鏡子
a mirror over here a mirror over here
這邊一個鏡子 這邊一個鏡子
wow you go in and see
哇 你走進去看
wow it's so big
哇 真的這麼大
In fact, this small corner
其實就這一小個角落這樣
very mirror very smart
很鏡子 很聰明
really big big
真的很大很大
Spray fire on this thing to go up like this
把這種東西噴火要上去這樣
why are you watching this
幹嘛看這個呢
I mean some people say it's a lie, right?
是說有人說這是騙人的 對不對
Do many of you know
你們是不是有很多人知道
say someone will say
說聽到會有人說
It's a scam, never been there
其實是騙局 根本沒有去過
Lie to you
騙你
Nope, I've heard of bureaucracy
沒有啦 有聽過的局勞
You must have heard of it, right?
應該都聽過是吧
good
好
Then what I want to say is of course
那我要講的當然是
Of course I've been there, don't be crazy
當然有去過 不要神經病
Is boring
很無聊
This is the process of middle age
這個是中年的過程
For example, this photo is famous
譬如這張照片很有名
Just for everyone to see
只是順便放給大家看
Here is this picture called Earthrise
這是這張照片叫Earthrise
Sunrise Earthrise
日升 地升
nor sunrise
也不是日升
not Moonrise
也不是月升
rising sun
日 地升
this is the surface of the moon
這是月球的表面
When actually orbiting the moon
實在繞月球的時候
photo taken by the astronaut
那個太空人拍的照片
This is of course
這個當然是
Boss Aubrey he is the second
Boss Aubrey他是第二個
man on the moon
站到月球上的人
he bowed his head
他自己低下頭來
He said the angle of this photo is too important
他說這張照片這個角度太重要了
take a snapshot
趕快照一張留下來
it's famous of course
這當然有名
possibly human
可能是人類的
Don't know if the third or fourth footprint
不知道第三個還是第四個腳印
this
這個
I see too many pictures like this
這種照片看多了
To be questioned is to say
被質疑就是說
where is this
這哪裡是這樣
this is the set
這就是片場
you are short
你少片了
You just take a photo on set
你就在片場裡拍一個照片
help us
拉扶我們
so you've been to the moon like this
所以你去過月球這樣
no evidence
無什麼證據
Then I can find a lot of holes
然後我還可以找到很多破綻
This is obviously something wrong with you
這個顯然你這個有不對
that's wrong
那個有不對
otherwise how could
要不然怎麼會
you can't explain
你解釋不清楚
obviously you lied
顯然你騙人
this is what we heard
這個就是我們聽到的這些
This argument
這種說法
Said that NASA has not actually been there
說NASA其實沒有去過
this is the set
這個是片場
Of course he told why
那當然他講出為什麼
I really don't want to repeat
我就真的很不想重複
Those concepts that those people say are wrong
那些人講的錯誤的那些概念
listen to you
給你們聽
because I'm wrong
因為我既然是錯誤的
why keep emphasizing
幹嘛一直去強調
but roughly
但是大致是
I can suggest some for you
我可以給你們提出來一些
Obviously you might find something weird
明明你會可能會覺得怪怪的東西
For example, it is dark
譬如說天是黑的
This is clearly under the sun
這明明就在大太陽底下
isn't that right, the sun is clearly over there
對不對 太陽顯然在那邊
And it's bright, no problem
而且很亮嘛 沒問題
the sun is over there
太陽就就在那邊
Why is the whole day dark
怎麼整個天都是黑的
It's obviously a scam.
顯然騙人騙錯了嘛
No, it's true. It should be black.
不是 是真天應該是黑的
Conversely, if this photo
反過來講 假如這個照片
If it's not dark here
這裡天不是黑的話
Soon we'll know he's a liar
馬上就 我們就知道他騙人
it should be dark
天應該是黑的
am i standing there
我就站在那裡嘛
you see the sun is bright
你看到太陽亮亮的
Of course it's bright
當然就是亮亮的
there is no sun
那邊也沒有太陽
how can it be bright over there
那邊怎麼會亮
Of course it's black
當然是黑的嘛
It's not bright, it's black
沒有亮就是黑的嘛
It's black over there too
那邊也是黑的嘛
Only that is bright, that's all
只有那個亮嘛 就這樣
Are you saying that this is not our experience?
你說這個好像不是我們的經驗嘛
Let's go outside during the day
我們走到白天走到外面去
The whole sky is bright
滿個天都是亮的啊
No, that's the earth, it's weird
不是啊 那個是地球很奇怪啦
It's not the moon, it's weird
不是月球很奇怪啦
What's so strange about the earth? Because it has air
地球有什麼奇怪?因為它有空氣
what you see is not the place that is glowing
你看到的不是那個地方在發亮
air scatters sunlight
是空氣把太陽光散射
become bright in all directions
變成所有方向都亮了
the whole day is bright
整個天都是亮的
that is the earth is strange
那是地球很奇怪
This is a function of the atmosphere
這個是大氣的一個作用
The role of air
空氣的作用
Including why the sky is blue
包括天為什麼會是藍的
That's the same reason
也就是同樣的道理
It's the details inside
就是它那個裡面細節裡面
you can analyze it
你都可以分析得出來
This was done more than a hundred years ago
這個在一百多年前就已經
people already know
人就已經知道了
This muyu scientist Raly
這個沐宇學家Raly
It's been proven
已經把這個都證明出來了
So it should be dark this day
所以這個天應該是黑的沒有錯
No one dares to say that you are a liar, right?
沒有人敢講說你騙人不是嗎
innocent is black
天真的是黑的
It's like using a black cloth behind a black studio
好像一個黑的片場後面用個黑布這樣
But it was questioned where did the star go?
可是被質疑過說那星星到哪兒去了?
Isn't there a star?
不是有星星嗎?
Aren't you bright? There should be bright spots
你不是就亮嗎?應該有亮點啊
Where did your bright spot go?
你這個亮點到哪裡去了?
Apparently your black cloth is too...too...
顯然你那個黑布太...太...
Didn't you just drill a few holes and cheat... then you couldn't cheat?
你當時鑽幾個洞不就騙...就騙不了了嗎?
No, because it's not easy for you to take pictures of those stars
不是這樣,因為你想要照那些星星都不太容易
Because this is too bright, like the sun, really under the big sun
因為這個太亮了,太陽一樣,真是大太陽底下
If you take out all the stars
你要是把星星都照出來的話
Your exposure time has long been exceeded
你的曝光時間早就超過了
throw it all away
這裡全部都擺掉
I can't take a photo
照不出來的啦
Yes, but I'm sorry, I can't take a picture
是有啦,但對不起,照不出來
In the Ganasa report when they came back
他們這些人回來的時候的那個Ganasa報告裡面
Many people have said that they see stars behind this photo
很多人都講到他們在這個面照後面有看到星星
You can barely see bright spots
很勉強可以看到有亮點
By the way, that's right
對了,是這樣
There is also a very interesting one that can be used as a joke
還有一個滿有趣的可以當作好笑的
it's called storytelling
這叫故事講的
it is this
是這個
This was also questioned
這個也被質疑過
And why is it like this on your ground?
而你這個地上怎麼是這樣
You go to the beach and get some sand rabbits on that set
你就去海邊弄一些沙兔在那片場裡
then step on it
然後去踩一下
wow that looks great
哇 好棒的樣子
another lie
又是騙人的
I'm telling you, I'm not lying
我跟你講 不是騙人
I'll tell you later
我等下告訴你
Why is it obviously not a lie
為什麼很明顯的不是騙人
this world is like this
這個世界是這樣
NASA people go before
NASA人去以前
What does this big lunar surface look like?
這個大大的月球表面是什麼樣
really do not know
真的不知道
because from a distance
因為遠遠看
even around
即使在繞
you can't see
你也看不出來
what does the moon look like
月面是什麼樣子
but does it matter what it looks like
但是什麼樣子有重要嗎
Very important
很重要
because you will log in in the future
因為你將來要登陸
that
那個
want
要
thump
噔
right
對不對
that Taiwanese boat
那個台灣艇
This landing craft is about to land
這個登陸艇要降落了
if that is hard ground
假如那個是很硬的地
rock
岩石
wow then you like this
哇 那你這樣
thump
噔一下不得了
I really don't want that
很不希望是這樣
Another is that the feet are not hard
還有一種是腳不是硬的
all it can't get you...no mud
全是它不得你...不會有泥巴
because there is no water
因為沒有水嘛
Otherwise it's sand
要不然是沙這種
that's even scarier
那更恐怖了
How many feet do you go up like this?
你幾顆腳這樣上去
Then it started to sink
然後就開始一直沉下去
That's even scarier, right?
那更恐怖了對不對
so this is very important
所以這個很重要
not kidding important
不是開玩笑的重要
is really important
是真的很重要
Then why might it be a hard ground?
那為什麼可能會是硬的地
It is of course possible
這是當然也可能
Because when it was first formed, it was
因為它當初形成的時候就是
Rocks were formed four billion years ago.
四十幾億年前形成的就是岩石嘛
then what
然後怎麼樣
has he always been a rock
它一直就是岩石嘛
Somebody go weather it into dirt?
有人去把它風化變成泥土嘛
No
沒有啊
Because there is no wind, no water, no air
因為沒風又沒水又沒空氣
it's hard
它就是硬的嘛
So that long didn't go before
所以那長沒有去以前
don't know what the surface looks like
並不知道表面是什麼樣子
must know
那必須要知道啊
Because I want someone to go
因為我要人要去啊
So let's go to the moon with an unmanned one first.
所以它先用無人的先登月試試看嘛
I found it good
結果我發現很好
not hard
也不是硬的
surface is dust
表面是粉塵
Not very thick
也沒有很厚一點點
wow this is the best
哇 這個是最棒
So take the back seat and follow that
所以往後座就按照那種
That kind of mechanics to do it, no problem, no problem at all
那種力學去做 沒問題 通通都沒問題
That is to say, the surface of the moon
也就是說 月球表面
really that's it
真的就是這樣
What is this being questioned?
這個被質疑是什麼呢 是
What's up with the surface of the moon?
月球表面怎麼這樣
why is this
為什麼會這樣
I don't know why it happened in the early days
哪有早期也不知道為什麼會這樣
Scientists slowly study and think slowly
科學家慢慢慢慢去研究 慢慢去想
later found out that
後來發現說
Since that's the case, let me explain
既然是這樣 讓我來解釋吧
explained
解釋的
Makes sense yes
講得通啦 是
this surface is
這個表面被
cosmic rays
宇宙射線
An example of solar wind charging
太陽風那種帶電的例子
Been fighting for billions of years
打了幾十億年了
It's all powdered
通通打成粉了
Molecule by molecule for you
一個分子一個分子給你打
That's how it was after the fight
打到後來就是這樣
It's not killing, it's not profit, it's like powder
這不是殺 不是利益的 是像粉一樣
I would just describe him as dust, that's all.
我就把他形容成粉塵嘛 就這樣
The surface is really like this
表面真的是這樣
and in that video
還有那個影片裡面
they're happy to go up
他們上去就很高興
Jumping over there, right?
在那邊跳跳這樣對不對
you have seen
你都看過
jump up and slowly fall down
跳起來就慢慢掉下來
Because of the gravity on this
因為這個上面的重力
Only one-sixth of the earth
只有地球上的六分之一
Of course you can jump high
當然跳起來可以跳很高
Then this one falls very slowly too
然後這個掉下來也很慢
If you kick this powder
假如是把這個粉踢一下的話
will definitely kick
一定會踢的
You will also kick when you go up
你上去裡面也會踢
i promise you
我給你保證
You can see the gray in the video
你就看到那影片裡面那個灰
That powder is like this
那個粉這樣
slow down like this
慢慢這樣下來
This is also questioned
這個也被質疑
why do this
為什麼要這樣
It's like there's air
這個好像有空氣才會這樣
Actually, what I want to answer is to say
其實我想回問的是說
what do you think it should be
那你覺得應該怎麼樣
as it should be
就應該這樣
no air
沒有空氣就這樣
if you say no
你假如說不是
then i know
那我知道說
and you
那你
I haven't read ordinary physics yet.
那普通物理還沒念好
many questions
很多問都
Actually, it's that kind, it's why it's so strange
其實是那種的,是說為什麼這樣很奇怪
It seems different from the earth, so you lie
好像跟地球上不一樣,所以你騙人
It's not like that, it's the other way around
其實不是這樣,是要反過來講
That's the truth, please think about it for yourself
是說真的就是這樣,你拜託你自己想想看
Why is this so? After thinking about it, it should be like this
為什麼是這樣,想通了再來講,應該是這樣
It should be treated like this
應該用這樣的態度去對待它
Everything is true in the lunar environment
所有的事情通通都是真的在月球的環境裡面
That's right, it's actually not easy to deceive people
是那個樣,這個想要騙人其實不太容易
You really have to do a scene and do everything
你真的要做一個場景,要做所有通通
It's all true, it looks weird
其實都是對的,看起來怪怪的
In fact, they are all right. In fact, it is very difficult to do. I won't lie to you.
其實都是對的,其實很難做到,我不騙你
It's really harder to do
真的更難做到的是
The moon landing started in 1961 when President Lee announced it on TV in public
登月從1961年剛才李總統當眾電視上宣布
Back then even the TV was a blackboard
那時候連電視都是黑板
announced on tv
電視上宣布說
Before the Coast of the Decade
我們Before the Coast of the Decade
before 1970
就是1970年以前
we're about to put a man on the moon
我們就要把人送上月球
and bring him back safely
然後很安全地把他帶回來
He will announce it to the world
他將全世界宣布這件事情
And he's saying I ordered NASA
而且他是說我命令NASA
Because NASA is the index of the presidential palace
因為NASA是指數總統府的
So he made the declaration
他就這樣講了這個宣示
At that time, it was still fighting on the moon
那時候還在打月戰
when i was working in america
我在美國工作的時候
some senior researchers
有一些資深的研究員
we sometimes chat
我們有時候聊天
they'll talk about that time
他們就會講到那個時候
They also saw it on TV
他們也是在電視上看到
How does our boss make such a declaration
我們的老闆怎麼做這種宣示
he's crazy
他發瘋了
Do you think that even the computer at that time
你想那個時候連電腦
nothing special
都不是什麼了不起的東西
there's nothing left
都沒有什麼了
he's crazy
他發神經病
how can we
我們怎麼可能
NASA
NASA
only three years old
才成立了三年
We'll be on the moon in a few years
我們幾年之內就登月
what are you kidding
開什麼玩笑
our boss is crazy
我們的老闆發瘋
Our senior man said
我們那個資深的人說
they were at that time
他們那個時候的
Just the people in NASA
就NASA裡面的人
their reaction is this
他們的反應是這樣
how about you go do it
怎麼樣 你去幹
results in less than eight years
結果不到八年
just landed on the moon
就登月了
this is
這個是
this you want me to imagine
這個你要我去想像
really can't imagine
真的想像不出來
how can it be so powerful
怎麼會這麼厲害
real
真的
when the power of the country is mobilized
動員國家的力量的時候
Wow
哇
the spirit of that america
那個美國的精神
really weird and powerful
真的很奇怪 很厲害
none
沒有一個
a nation
一個民族
or a group
或一個團體
can do this
可以做到這樣
really weird
真的很奇怪
America is not the first time
美國還不是第一次
Find a few more years in the 20th World War
再找幾年在二十大戰的時候
Made it in three years
三年就做出來
it's hard
簡直很難
it's really hard to imagine
這真的很難想像
But how many years do you think this matter has invested a total of 100,000 people?
不過你以為這個事情整個從多少年投入了總共有十萬人
At that time, there were 100,000 people on Pangda Road
就那時候龐大道有十萬人
There are only 30,000 people now
現在只有三萬人
How much money will the country go down
國家多少錢下去
mobilize so much force
動員這麼大的力量
did it and succeeded
做到後來做成功了
Do you think if this is a lie
你覺得假如這個是騙
you want the whole thing to be a lie
你想要整個都是騙人
want to face the truth
想要淹面事實
then fake
然後造假騙人
It can still deceive people on such a large scale
做這麼大規模還繼續能騙人
the degree of difficulty
那個難的程度
you might as well go
還不如你就去吧
real
真的
that is difficult
那個才難
it's not that hard for you to go
你就去沒有這麼難
think from this angle
從這個角度想
In fact it is true
其實真的是這樣
I give you another test
我給你另外一個試證
maybe you know
也許你就知道
right
對啦
you've been there
你一直去過啦
this thing
是這個事情喔
You need to know the meaning behind them
你要知道他們的背後的意義
Just run white rice to see who wins
就是跑白米看誰贏
who lost
輸的是誰啊
Soviet Union
蘇聯欸
People in the Soviet Union never said a word
蘇聯的人講過一句話沒有
No
沒有
You know you're fake if you lose
你知道輸掉假你是造假的喔
Who are you going to lie to?
你要騙誰啊
The Soviet Union is full of experts
蘇聯那邊都是專家欸
experts among experts
專家中的專家欸
you got any fake stuff in here
你這裡面有任何假的東西
He's not the first to tell you to lie less.
他不是第一個跟你講的少騙啊
No
沒有啊
Who is now talking about the United States?
是誰現在在講是美國裡面的
You go and look through those people in the future
你去仔細翻一翻那些人將來
The more he talks the more money he makes
講越多他會賺越多錢
i will lie to you
我會騙你
write more books
寫越多書
more tv
上越多電視
The whole world invites him everywhere
全世界到處邀請他去風光
i will lie to you
我會騙你
You will know why this kind of thing happens
你就知道為什麼會有這種事情了
If you have ever been deceived
你們假如曾經被迷惑過的話
I guess you have enough curiosity
算你們有足夠的好奇心
but sorry
可是對不起
you are curious because you are curious
你好奇是你好奇
fact or fact
事實還是事實
This matter can be analyzed later
這個事情可以把這樣的分析過以後
No matter what angle you say about dry shoes
不管你說枯鞋的角度
Is it human long-term love? Look at it from this angle
是不是人的長情去這個角度去看
Don't worry, I've been there
不用擔心啦 有去過啦
it's all true
都是真的啦
OK this is the last one
OK 這是最後一張
that is to say
是這樣就是說
Well, I was there at that time
好啦 那個時候去過
You know you've been there six times and you've been there at six o'clock
你知道去過六次有六個點都去過
There are instruments at six points
在六個點都有儀器
There is the same path that the car on the moon surface traveled.
都有當初那個月面車子走過的路徑
There are traces all over
痕跡通通都有
after decades
經過幾十年了
are those things still there
那些東西還在嗎
of course in
當然在
because there is no wind and rain
因為沒有風吹雨打
what was he like when he left
他當初走的時候什麼樣
It's the same now. It hasn't changed.
現在就是那個樣 沒變過
Then can we take a sneak peek?
那我們是不是可以去偷偷看一下呢
Can
可以
in 2009
在2009年的時候
The United States sent a purpose not to see
美國發了一個目的不是去看
this original scene
這個當初的場景
It's just some scientific satellites that we really want to explore.
就是真的去探閱的一些科學的衛星
The spaceship is called the Lunar Reconnaissance Orbiter
太空船叫做Lunar Reconnaissance Orbiter
just went
就去了
Going around is going around without logging in
去了是繞 沒有登錄 就在繞
into my process
到我的過程當中
Of course those spacecraft have good cameras
那種太空船當然有很好的照相機
Which means NASA, of course, has a schedule
就是說NASA當然就排好排定
Someday you will fly to our original
你哪一天會飛到我們當初
Above the login point on the 11th
11號的登錄點上空
you take our picture back
你給我們照相回來
Someday you will fly to the position of No. 14
哪一天你會飛到第14號的那個位置
Come back if you take a picture of me
你給我照相也回來
6 dots, 7 dots, all 6 dots are covered
6個點 7個點都 六個點都照到了
All six points are taken
六個點通通都照到了
Here are two examples
這是兩個例子
this is
這個是
left is
左邊是
11th is the first time
11号是第一次
over there is number 14
那边是14号
Can you see a bright spot here
能不能看到这里有一个亮点
the sun comes from here
太阳从这边来
here is a bright spot
这里有个亮点
its shadow is elongated
它的影子是长形的
This thing is an upright tall thing
这一个东西是直立的高的东西
definitely not natural
绝对不是天然物
Natural things don't look like this
天然物没有长这样
except on earth
除了在地球上有
because when the wind blows and the rain
因为风吹雨时
time-lapse of that terrain
那个地形的延时
It's possible to look long
长的样是有可能
That's what happens after erosion
那是侵蚀过以后才会那样
normally it grows into
正常它长成
don't grow anything like this
不会长出这样的东西
here has
这里有
This is the point of the light path
这个就是那个灯路的点
and see
而且看到
An upright thing with such a long shadow
这个影子这么长的一个直立的东西
It's the Luna
就是它灯月体
this is stone town
这个是石镇
that thing is still there
那个东西还在
Then you're a liar besides this
那你除了就连这个都是骗人的
All right
好吧
This is on the 14th side
这个是14号那边
look carefully
你仔细看
Can you see there's a
你能不能看到这里有一个
There is that trace on this surface
這個表面有那個痕跡
this is a spaceship
這是太空船
space this one will go
太空這個會走的那個
What is a small car
什麼叫就是一個小車子
out of the track
走出來的軌跡
go put that instrument here
去放那個儀器放在這裡
there are instruments
這裡還有儀器
This shadow is also like this
這個影子也是這樣的
this is current affairs
這個是時政
This is over 30 years
這個是經過了30多年
stay safe
別來無恙
really still
真的還在
There is no need to keep saying this
這個不用去一直說
i want now
我現在想要
not talking about me
不是說我啦
what do you want to prove
那時候想要證明什麼
nope
也不是啦
I told you back then that I never reacted
那時候我跟你講從來沒有反應過
no public announcement
沒有對外宣稱
didn't come out and say
沒有跑出來說
Let me testify
我來端證一下視聽
we have been there
我們真的有去過啦
I didn't say a word back then
那時候一句話都沒講過
never said
從來沒講過
It's just that the official didn't say it back.
就是官方沒有講回去
i think it's right
我覺得是對的
casual talk
民間隨便去講
i don't care about you
我懶得理你
what do you mean
那個意思啦
Really, you ignore him instead
真的你去理他反而
not like NASA
不像是NASA
right
對不對
I dignified NASA
我堂堂NASA
I don't care what you say
我管你去講什麼
i have it
我有就是有
I follow these
我照這些
not for
也不是為了要
to refute you
要駁斥你
I just want to take pictures
我就是要照
How about it
怎麼樣
I just want to see the situation
我就是要看當時的情況
This is the last trace left
這個是最後留下的痕跡
that's the end of my story
那我故事就講到這裡
Because of the moon you all start
因為月亮你們大家都開始
understand better
多一點理解了吧
We humans probably know this too.
我們人類大概也知道這樣而已啦
ok thank you all
好謝謝大家
Thank you so much
非常感謝
i think we really are
我想我們真的是
one night
一個晚上的
not talking about night
不是講夜
Learn more about the moon
不但瞭解月亮多一點
I also heard many stories
也聽了很多很多的故事
then we are left
那我們剩下
about twenty minutes
二十分鐘左右
let everyone ask questions
讓大家提問
Doesn't China also have Tibet-Cooperative Moon Exploration?
中國不是也有藏合探月嗎?
right
對
talk about
講一講
this right
這個對
In fact, if we say that this lunar exploration has been very quiet since 1972
其實假如說這個探月從1972年以後其實就很安靜了
Because what I just said is that there's nothing to go on
因為我剛剛講的就是沒有什麼好再去
sooner or later
遲早還是要去
Because you are curious about science
因為居然科學你也有好奇心
During the Cold War, Japan actually had
這個冷戰期間其實日本有
These are small satellites
這個都是很小的衛星
even some are for experiments
就是甚至有些是做實驗用的
have been there
就有去過
It really only started in the last few years
真的到了最近幾年才開始
go back and say
又回頭去說
we're going back to the moon
我們要重返月球
have you heard the slogan
有沒有聽過這個口號
that is to say
那個是認為是說
It is to do this from the perspective of scientific exploration
是要用科學探索的角度去做這件事
Well, I did make a statistic here.
那我這邊確實有做了一個統計
But the reason we have it is because it was years ago
但是我們有放的原因是因為這是好幾年前的
look what's over here
你看這邊是什麼
It's not when you read my writing
寓計不是你看我這邊寫的時候
It was already a few years ago
就已經是幾年前的事情了
Actually quite a lot
其實蠻多的
Europe also went
歐洲也去了
Japan went to the United States several times
日本又去了美國去了好幾次
Including most of China and Russia
包括中國大多長俄
I'm only going for the first time as I write
我在寫的時候只是第一次去
It's just Chang'e No. 1
長俄一號而已
Number three should be gone by now, right?
現在應該三號都去了對不對
that's gone
那個在人都去了
haven't landed on the moon yet
還沒有登月還沒有登
go to the moon
登月
But it will be more and more lively in the future, it's true
但是將來會越來越熱鬧這是這是真的
Even India is going to go
連印度都要去都去了
So this moon has become a new one
所以這個月亮已經變成一個新的
Not a Cold War target anymore
不是冷戰的目標了
but
而是
It's probably for the purpose of showing national strength.
大概是展現國力的目標了
But unfortunately it still seems to be a goal
但是很不幸的好像還是一個目標而已
Let me ask, the bigger the animal on the earth, the magnetic ring it walks on, like an elephant,
我請問一下,地球上的動物越大,就是走路的磁環,像大象的話,
Obviously, there is no way to jump as high as an explosion, or as high as a jumping claw,
顯然就沒辦法像爆,或者像跳爪跳那麼高嘛,
Could it be that the earth used to rotate faster, so it has more centrifugal force,
那是不是地球以前轉得比較快,所以比較有離心力,
Then the moon is on it again, and it is pulling, so the dinosaurs more than 100 million years ago can grow to be so big,
然後月球又在上面,在拉,所以一億多年前的恐龍,可以長到那麼大,
Then after the dinosaurs died out, it would be better if you couldnt grow up to be as big as a dinosaur,
那後來恐龍滅亡以後,不如你就沒辦法長到像恐龍那麼大,
Because the earth rotates relatively slowly now, there is no centrifugal force.
因為地球現在轉得比較慢了嘛,所以沒有離心力。
In this way, what you think of this seems to be quite interesting qualitatively,
這樣子講,這個你想的到是在定性上好像蠻有趣,
However, this should not be the case in terms of quantification. That is to say, you just mentioned these phenomena,
但是在定量上面應該不是這樣,就是說你剛剛講到這些現象,
We actually understand it, I will describe it a little later,
我們其實是理了解的,我待會稍微形容一下,
But the phenomenon you mentioned, in fact, no matter how fast our centrifugal force is on the earth, you actually dont feel it.
但是你講到那個現象,其實在地球上我們的離心力再快,其實你也沒有感覺到。
That centrifugal force is now only 1/300 of Wanyous profit.
那個離心力現在來講只有萬有盈利的三百分之一而已
not yet
都還不到
no matter how fast you earn
你賺得再快
That's like one hundredth
那譬如說是一百分之一
that's going to happen soon
那快得不得了啦
That's like one hundredth of gravity
也譬如說只有重力的一百分之一
That's only one hundredth
那也只有一百分之一
How big can that grow for animals
那個對動物能長多大
that effect is too small
那個影響實在太小了
Then you say that the difference between animals is several times
那你說動物的差別是好幾倍
several times
好幾倍了
That's only one percent off
那個只差百分之一而已
It is really
實在是
negligible
微不足道
So it has nothing to do with that reason
所以跟那個原因沒有關係
how fast with that
跟那個轉多快
it doesn't matter
這個都沒有關係
Then why did dinosaurs grow so big
那為什麼恐龍可以長這麼大
We can now also fear
我們現在也可以恐
If you bite a dinosaur now, it can be this big
現在咬一咬恐龍的話也可以這麼大
but you'll find it's really slow
但是你會發現它確實動作很慢
Even an elephant can say it's slow
連大象都可以說它動作很慢
Moves very slowly compared to Jumping Claw
比起跳爪來動作很慢
The jumping claw is dozens of times taller than its own body
跳爪自己身子的幾十倍高
Or an elephant, or if you are on the road in a powerful scene, or something with a big road, just jump off
或是大象,或者你在厲害的場景路,或路很大的東西,就跳下去
This is not, it has nothing to do with whether the earth rotates or not
這個不是,這跟地球有沒有轉,這個沒有關係
This is because under our gravity
這個是因為我們這個重力情況之下
The bigger the thing, its volume, for example, you magnify me ten times
越大的東西,它體積,譬如說你把我放大十倍
My weight has changed a thousand times, but my feet have only grown a hundred times
體重變一千倍,但是我的腳只有一百倍出
This is two-dimensional space, the volume is three-dimensional space
這是二度空間,體積是三度空間
You magnify me ten times, you see I am big, and my feet are a hundred times bigger
你把我放大十倍,你看我很大,腳也出了一百倍
But sorry, I'm a thousand times heavier
但是對不起,我的體重重了一千倍
do you think i can stand still
你覺得我還能站得住嗎?我自己都垮掉了
So what should I do? Then my legs will be thicker
所以怎麼辦呢?那我腿要更粗啊
It can't be enlarged so thick according to my scale.
不能照我這個比例放大那麼粗啊
Elephants are like this, you see their legs are so thick
大象就這樣,你看它腿大到粗
seems out of proportion
好像不成比例
That is to say, you dance him
也就是說你把他跳著
Speechless, ask him to zoom in
無言無語就要他放大
don't say he dances
不要說他跳
he can't even stand
他連站都站不住
his thin feet
他那腳細細的
so in that movie
所以那個電影裡面
how to explode
怎麼炸猛
mouse so big
老鼠這麼大
don't be afraid
那不要怕
he won't eat you
他不會吃你
he can't even stand
他連站都站不住
this is just
這個只是
The difference between two tails and three tails
二尾跟三尾的差別
There are actually many examples of this
這種例子其實很多
we look up at the sky
我們看天空上去
because of the sky
因為這個天空
this space
這個太空
air this
空中這個
Microparticle
微粒子的
spectrum turns blue
spectrum變成藍色
on the night ball
在夜球上面
see what color it is
看回來是什麼顏色
good question
好問題
We see the blue of the sky is
我們看到天空的藍色是
in our big air
我們這個大空氣裡的
The solution to scattering sunlight
把太陽光上散射的解決
if you look from the outside
假如你是從外面看
Actually you can't see the air
其實你是看不到空氣的
it is transparent
它是透明的
we are in this because
我們是因為在這個裡面
it fan shot
它這個扇射
it fanned in
它是往裡面扇射
not outside
不是往外面
outside is getting thinner
外面是越來越稀薄
from the outside
從外面看
good question
這個問題很好
when viewed from the outside
從外面看的時候
In fact, the air is transparent
其實空氣是透明的
no air in sight
看不到空氣
but we can see
但是我們可以看到
clouds in the air
空氣裡面的雲
clouds are white water
雲就是白白的水
water molecule
水分子
it's not by fanning
它不是靠扇射
it is reflection
它就是反射
It's just a group of white clouds
就是白白的雲一群一群一群
elsewhere is
其他地方就是
If you don't see the land
沒有就看到陸地了
or the sea
或者海
that's all
就這樣
did not see
也沒有看到
also can't see what color it should be
也看不出它應該是什麼顏色
On the whole
那整體來講
our earth
我們的地球
Nicknamed Blue Planet
綽號叫做Blue Planet
mean blue planet
意思是藍色的行星
That blue is not because of the air
那藍色不是因為有空氣
It's the reflection of sea water
是就是海水的反射
there is another reason
那有另外一個原因
why is the sea blue
海水為什麼是藍色
That's another reason, but it's really blue
這是另外一個原因,但是確實是藍的
70% of the earth is water
地球基本上70%都是水
So the earth as a whole looks like a blue shape from the outside.
所以地球整體從外面看是一個藍色的形形
Please tell me, you said that the earth is also angry with the moon
請教一下,你說地球對月球也有朝氣現象
This means that the interior of the moon is not solid either.
意思就是說月球的內部也是不是固體的
That's a good question, the moon we think it's something that's cooled
這個問題很好,這個月球我們認為它是已經冷掉的東西
But it is completely solid, why does a solid have friction?
但是完全是固體的,固體為什麼還會有摩擦
The answer is yes, solids still have friction
答案是對,固體還是有摩擦
Because the energetic society outside is actually pinching and pulling it with images like this
因為這個外面這個朝氣力會其實是在有影像把它捏拉捏拉這樣子
In this molecule and molecule, there is actually a mole-mole movement.
在這個分子跟分子中其實也是摩來摩去的
That's how Momo energy is consumed
就是那樣摩摩能量就會被消耗
So this optical translation is friction
所以這個光譯的也就是摩擦
So don't look at his hard one still inside
所以不要看他硬硬的一個照樣在裡面
Just now there were earthquakes and moonquakes
剛剛那個還有地震還有月震
are the result of this force
都是這種作用力下的結果
Ask Professor Zhao
請教趙教授
The one who read the report that there was a sign of water found on Mars
那個曾經看過報導說火星上有發現水的那個跡象
also have air
也有空氣
So it's a bit similar to the conditions on Earth.
所以跟地球的條件有點雷同
Very suitable for human migration to Mars
很適合人類移居住到火星上去
Ask Professor Zhao for your opinion
請教趙教授您的看法
Thanks
謝謝
good question
是個好問題
But you want me to live, I don't think so
但是你要我去住我覺得不去
Because what you said is very suitable is actually just a relative
因為你說很合適其實只是一個相對的
Which means he's at least not as hot as the sun
就是說他至少沒有像太陽這麼熱
Or maybe the pressure isn't as great as Jupiter's
或者是壓力沒有像木星這麼大
Or maybe he doesn't have that much gravity
或者是他重力沒有那麼強
i can stand up
我可以站起來
It's okay in terms of
來講都還可以
Because Mars is the size of Earth
因為火星跟地球大小
not too much difference
沒有差太多
so its
所以它的
the gravity you are on
你在上面受到的重力
smaller than the earth
比地球要小一點
Great
很好啊
people go to dream shape
人家到夢形上去
you can't stand
你站都站不住
just go down
就垮下去
that gravity is too much
那個重力太大
there are others
那還有其他
it has air
它有空氣
but sorry for its air
可是對不起它的空氣
all carbon dioxide
全部都是二氧化碳
you can't breathe
你不能呼吸的
its temperature
它的溫度呢
kill you
人死你
because it is far
因為它很遠
and the earth is far away
而且地球很遠
and
而且
Even if it's all carbon dioxide
即使全部都是二氧化碳
its
它的
greenhouse effect
溫室效應
only raise it to
只把它提高到
Some
一些
still too cold
還是更太冷
Of course the air is only of the earth
當然空氣只有地球的
Less than 10%
10%都不到
very thin
很稀薄的
is there any water
那還有沒有水
Now there is no liquid water on the surface
現在表面上找不到液體的水
because it's too cold
因為太冷啊
it maybe that
它也許那個
Soil can't be called soil
土壤也不能叫土壤
The weathered sand
當初被風化過的那些沙
Those substances may have frozen moisture in them
那些物質裡面可能有凍結的水分
might have
可能有
In particular, there is a lot of dry ice in the North and South Poles
尤其南北極還有很多乾冰
it's cold
就是很冷的情況
Does that mean it's a good place for people to live?
那樣是不是叫做很合適人去居住
In fact, it can be said that you go up
其實是可以這麼說你上
I don't talk about you
我不說你啊
you put a person on it
你把放一個人放在上面
He died in three minutes
三分鐘他就死掉了
he can't be hot
他絕對不能火的
Then you say I want to build something
那你就說我要蓋一個什麼
The airtight environment keeps fire inside
密閉的環境讓它裡面存火
of course you can
那當然可以
then you can also be on the moon
那你在月球上也可以
The elite can't come up with it
精英心上來不行
too hot to kill you
太熱 熱死你
Look at it from your fake angle
就你假意這個角度去看
Oh well
那好吧
That Mars is
那火星算是
If you must leave the distance
你一定要遺距的話
you choose him, you don't choose anything else
你就選他 你不要選別的
It's not that he's good, other things are worse
不是說他好是別的更爛
The professor just heard that the earth will turn slower and slower because the power of his feet is absorbed by the moon
教授就是剛才有聽到說地球會越轉越慢是因為他的腳動力被月球吸收
Then there is a question that I didnt understand just now, why is he always seeing the same side of the moon
然後有一個疑問就是剛剛沒有聽懂的就是為什麼永遠看到月球的都是他同一面
Then why is it because the moon is no longer spinning, so he can see the same side of him
那為什麼會是因為月球他不再轉了轉不動所以才看到他的同一面
It's not because the power of his feet is absorbed by the moon, why isn't the moon turning faster and faster
不是因為他的腳動力若被月球吸收為什麼不是月球會越轉越快
Great question for this question this has a strong physics concept
對這個問題問得太棒了這個有物理很強的物理概念
I was just secretly wanting to... just... pass the door like this
我剛才只是偷偷偷想要...就...門混過關這樣
In fact, this means that the foot momentum is taken away by him, so shouldnt he turn faster and faster?
其實是這樣就是說腳動量被他拿去了那他不是應該越轉越快嗎
If it's fast, it's not... sooner or later I'll see behind him
一快的話不就是不...我就遲早會看到他後面
This didn't happen because
沒有這樣發生 原因是
the shape of the moon
這個月球的形狀
Has been sucked into a very strange shape by our earth
已經被我們地球吸成一個很奇怪的形狀
It's not that you think it's weird when you see it, it's not weird
不是說你一看就覺得奇怪 不是奇怪
It still begs for a ball
它還是求求一個球嘛
look inside carefully
仔細看裡面
it becomes a bit out of shape
它有一點變成離形
it faces the earth
它朝著地球這邊
It turned out to be like the one in Zhongbai
原來像中百那個
this is the lowest one
這是最低的那個
You can say Veen, Gravity Veen
你可以說衛能 重力衛能
its shape has been taken by the earth
它形狀已經被地球
It seems to be frozen
好像動住 凍結住了
so it just
所以它就
when you go around like this
這樣繞的時候
it's very comfortable
它就很舒服嘛
Now you have to force it to turn faster
那你現在要強迫它轉快一點
In fact, there is another force
其實又有一個力
want to pull it back
想要把它扯回來
So now put in an extra effort
所以現在又多出一個力來
or Earth's tidal forces
還是地球的潮汐力
please don't turn
拜託你不要轉
because you like facing me
因為你不是喜歡對著我嗎
Because this shape already looks like this
因為這個形狀已經這個樣啦
So its final result is
所以它最後的結果是
it's still like this
它還是這個樣
But the foot momentum is still there
可是腳動量還是拿到了
what about it
它怎麼辦
The result of this balance of forces is that everyone starts to turn in a big circle, just like that
這個力的平衡的結果是大家就開始轉大圈,就這樣
It is said that NASA has taken photos of aliens, is this really the case?
傳說NASA有拍到外星人的照片,那真的有這個嗎?
Who said NASA ever took pictures of aliens?
誰說NASA曾經拍過外星人的照片?
no , you smash that tv
沒有啦,你把那電視砸掉
If there is really a TV saying that, you can really sue him for slander or nonsense
假如真的有電視這樣講,你真的可以去告他污衊或亂講
So I'm someone who used to be NASA, I want to really blow him up
以我是曾經是NASA的人,我還想真的去炸他
It's a joke of course, but the point is you don't really don't say anything
這當然是開玩笑,但是重要點是你不要真的不要講什麼
Just do what you say, no, you have to make your own judgment
你講什麼你就這樣,不行的,你要有自己的判斷
how to judge
判斷怎麼來
listen to speeches more
多去聽演講
That nonsense is too much
那個亂講的實在太多了
we have one more question ok
我們還有一個問題好不好
let him that one
讓他那一位
Hello Professor I have a very curious question
教授您好我有一個很好奇的問題
These are the names you mentioned just now
就是您剛剛講到精心水心目心這些名稱
Why is it so consistent with the names of the five elements we Chinese talk about?
為什麼跟我們中國人講的五行的名稱是這麼一致啊
how is this so consistent
這怎麼這麼一致
not this is the same thing
不是這個是同一回事
That is to say, we are the same as the ancients
就是說我們古人一樣
now people are the same
現在人一樣
If you want to find planets in the sky
你假如要在天上找到行星
The planets are recognizable
行星是可以認得出來了
because it can run
因為它是會跑的
The other stars are always a place
其他的星都永遠是一個位置
You can watch it move when you turn it yourself
你自己在轉就看它整個在動
But planets relative to other stars
可是行星相對於其他的星
it is moving
它是在動
moving so close to me
離我那麼近在動
You can see that its position is moving relative to other stars every day
你可以看到它每天位置都相對於其他星都在跑
In fact, in English, the word Planet means a heart that can run
實際上那個英文,那個Planet這個字就是會跑的心的意思
Then let's say translated into planets, it will go
那我們就說翻譯成行星,它會走
People in ancient times were not called planets, they were called Huo Xing, Huo who was confused
古時候的人不是叫行星,叫做霍星,迷霍的霍
because I really don't know why it moves
因為我真的搞不清楚它為什麼會動
Others are not moving, this fan
其他都沒有在動啊,這迷霍
Even if we were in history, you are the same now
就是我們在歷史上,你現在也是一樣
You go to the sky to find Huo Xing, you can find five
你要去天上找霍星,可以找到五個
can be seen with the naked eye
用肉眼就可以看到
The Chinese people's method is five, well, gold and wood follow Huo Tu
中國人的辦法就是五個,好,金木隨霍土
Who? Who is gold, that yellow one is called gold, that gold star
誰啊?誰是金,那個黃黃的叫金,那個金星
Who is wood, who is fire, that spark is fire
誰是木,誰是火,那個火星就是火
because it's red
因為它紅紅的
Who is the water, the white one
誰是水,那個白白的那個
It's Mercury, the other two are Jupiter and Saturn
就是水星,另外兩個一個木星一個土星
This is how it came about, because we originally had the concept that gold and wood follow Huo Tu
是這樣來的,是我們原來就有金木隨霍土的概念
and saw five guys in the sky
然後看到天上有五個傢伙
Then give him a checkmark
那就給他一個一個對號
Then we have the concept of yin and yang
然後我們還有陰陽的概念
that's even better sun moon
那更好了 太陽月亮
All seven guys got it right
七個傢伙全部都對了
Then this lived happily for thousands of years
然後這個就很高興的活了好幾千年
until the nineteenth and eighteenth centuries
一直到十九十八世紀
the telescope is out
望遠鏡出來了
see not only five but six and seven
看到不只五個 有六個 有七個
There are eight, even the earth is one
有八個 連地球也是一個
So what to do, this is completely broken
那怎麼辦 這個就被完全就打破了
It's our original philosophy
就是我們原來的那種哲學的
This arrangement doesn't actually work
這種安插 其實不 work
No, we now know that's not right
不對 那我們現在也了解那樣不對
just a coincidence
只是巧合就這樣
So those names come from
所以那些名字是這樣來的
rather than just
而不是說剛好
you just follow him
你就是按照他這樣去取
So how do we name the new discovery?
那新發現的我們怎麼取名字呢
i run out
我用光啦
just use
只要用
Just use English or what Westerners call you
就用英文或者是西方人叫什麼名字
I just translate the meaning
我就翻譯意思就好了
Urnus is the king of heaven
Urnus就是天王嘛
Is Nephtune really the god of the sea?
Nephtune真的是海神嘛
It's Aquaman
就是海王嘛
Is Proctor really that Yama of Hell?
Protor真的是地獄那個閻羅王嘛
It's King Ming
就是明王嘛
The name came from outside
這個名字是從外面來的
Then we originally gave the golden wood decaying European soil
那我們原來給的金木衰歐土
Foreigners also have these five names
洋人也有這五個也都有名字
They don't call gold, wood and Europe
他們不叫金木衰歐土
He called this this this this this this
他叫這個這個這個這個這個
Then we now say Venus is Vinus
那我們現在說金星就是Vinus
Mars is Mars
火星就是Mars
it's the same thing
這是同一個東西
that name is different
那名字又不一樣
It was different
本來就不一樣嘛
It's almost a process like this
差不多是這樣的一個過程
we really enjoyed it tonight
我們今天晚上真的是很享受喔
Everyone go out later
待會大家出去
At least I saw the moon when I came
至少我來的時候有看到月亮
when you go out to see the moon
出去看到月亮的時候
do you feel different
有沒有覺得不一樣
Uh uh thanks everyone
呃 呃 大家一起感謝
Thanks
謝謝
good teacher
好 國師